<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Household Cookery and Laundry Work</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Cookbooks and herbals</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div n="6" type="contents">
         <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
            <item><ref target="#intro">Introduction</ref>,. . . . . . . . . <num>7</num></item>
            <item><ref target="#soups">Soups</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . . <num>11</num></item>
            <item><ref target="#fish">Fish</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . . <num>24</num></item>
            <item><ref target="#meat">Meat</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . . <num>32</num></item>
            <item><ref target="#veg">Vegetables</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . <num>58</num></item>
            <item><ref target="#puddings">Puddings</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . <num>68</num></item>
            <item><ref>Sauces</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . . <num>91</num></item>
            <item><ref>Cakes and Baking</ref>, . . . . . . . . <num>95</num></item>
            <item><ref>Sick-Room Cookery</ref>, . . . . . . . . <num>109</num></item>
            <item><ref>Beverages</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . <num>115</num></item>
            <item><ref>Preserves</ref>, . . . . . . . . . . <num>123</num></item>
            <item><ref>Miscellaneous</ref>, . . . . . . . . . <num>128</num></item>
            <item><ref>Laundry Work</ref>, . . . . . . . . . <num>129</num></item>
         </list>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="intro" xml:id="intro">
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>A GREAT deal more of a country's prosperity depends 
            upon comfortable homes than philosophers might be
            willing to acknowledge; for people cannot prosecute
            business with great energy, or study with much enjoy-
            ment or profit, if there are worries at home, or muddle
            and discomfort there. This is quite apparent to all, and
            thought it seems a matter of minor importance com-
            pared with the great interests and objects that have
            to be carried on out of doors, yet if the household
            machinery is out of order or not moving smoothly,
            the derangement may be carried forward till very
            important interests are disturbed.</p>
            <p>   The home is the nursery of the present and future
            inhabitants of a country, and the care of the home
            devolves generally upon woman—in our country, at
            all events, it does so universally; and by the manner
            in which she performs her most important duties, not
            only the present comfort, but, it may be, the future
            destinies of the inmates may be influenced, if not
            moulded. Incapacity on her part leads to many certain
            evils—disorder, waste, and muddle; and may have still
            worse effects on the health and tempers of the family.
            Whatever other duties a woman may have, she must
            either manage her house herself, or devolve the care of
            it upon some other woman; consequently all women
            should be carefully trained for this their occupation.</p>
            <p>   Parents would never think of setting a young man
            up in business unless he had been trained, probably by
            a long apprenticeship; and yet it has been practically
            decided by many people that a young woman in-
            stinctively knows all about housekeeping; that she
            can cook without being taught, and can manage a
            house and instruct servants without ever having
            studied the subject of domestic management; that if
            she has received a liberal education and some know-
            ledge of needlework, everything else necessary to set
            her up as the mistress of a house comes naturally.
            Good mothers do and have always done great things
            in training their daughters, but many girls have not
            that advantage; and even mothers may see the neces-
            sity of their best instructions being supplemented.</p>
            <p>   Happily most people are now alive to the necessity
            of training girls of all classes for their natural and
            certain occupation—the care of the home; and
            domestic economy and cookery, instead of being
            shunted aside and picked up by degrees how and where
            they can be, are now prominent branches of instruction,
            and few girls of any rank finish their education
            without these branches being studied.</p>
            <p>   This little book proposes to be a practical guide to
            some departments of domestic management in a plain
            household,—namely, in Cookery, Laungry Work, and
            Household Management. Ignorance of these subjects
            has caused many a young housekeeper headaches and
            heartaches; and only after many trials and much
            waste has she succeeded in learning duties which a
            little early training would have made quite easy.</p>
            <p>   Perhaps the most important result of this training
            is, that a knowledge of the constituents of different
            classes of food is acquied, and children may be fed
            with suitable food, which so greatly promotes health,
            and thus sent out to fight the world's battles with the
            sound, healthy bodies which so greatly assist the sound
            mind; for improper or unsuitable food generally
            impairs health or saps its foundations; and want of
            health impairs very greatly the energy and usefulness,
            as well as the individual happiness.</p>
            <p>   The recipes given have all been repeatedly worked
            by the writer, and are perfectly reliable, and purposely
            made so plain that very young people can easily follow
            them. There are only a few specimens of the different
            classes of recipes given, because, with a little experi-
            ence and practice, they may be varied and altered to 
            a great extent to suit the circumstances of the house-
            hold; they are moderately economical, and, if necessary,
            can be made more so.</p>
            <p>   Three different constituents must enter into the
            daily food of all to supply the waste and the wants
            of the human body, and keep all the organs in good
            working order — Nitrogenous, Carbonaceous, and
            Mineral Foods.</p>
            <p>   Nitrogenous food forms flesh and muscle and sup-
            plies strength; carbonaceous food gives heat and acts
            as the fuel to the engine; mineral food is necessary for
            the formation and repair of bone, and is an important
            constituent of the blood.</p>
            <floatingText>
            <body>
               <div>
                  <head>PRINCIPAL NITROGENOUS FOODS, OR FLESH-FORMERS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>ANIMAL.</head>
                     <item>Butcher Meat.</item>
                     <item>Poultry.</item>
                     <item>Fish.</item>
                     <item>Eggs.</item>
                     <item>Cheese. Milk.</item>
                  </list>
                  <cb/>
                  <list>
                     <head>VEGETABLE.</head>
                     <item>Flour.</item>
                     <item>Oatmeal.</item>
                     <item>Peas.</item>
                     <item>Beans.</item>
                     <item>Lentils.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>CARBONACEOUS OR BODY-WARMING FOODS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>ANIMAL.</head>
                     <item>Butter.</item>
                     <item>Suet.</item>
                     <item>Oil.</item>
                     <item>Fat.</item>
                  </list>
               <cb/>
               <list>
                  <head>VEGETABLE.</head>
                  <item>Sugar.</item>
                  <item>Treacle.</item>
                  <item>Rice.</item>
                  <item>All starchy foods.</item>
               </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>MINERAL FOODS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Green Vegetables.</item>
                     <item>Wheat and Oatmeal.</item>
                     <item>Water. Milk.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Those three constituents, which ought to enter into
            the daily food of all, are to be found in plain ordinary
            materials, and, as will be seen by the foregoing table,
            in vegetable as well as in animal food.</p>
            <p>   Animal food is by no means an absolute necessity,
            and may, with advantage to health in many cases, be
            enitrely dispensed with. The nitrogenous principle in
            vegetable food is not so concentrated as in animal
            food, and consequently a larger bulk is required to
            procure the same amount of strength. Persons who
            have plenty of work or exercise in the open air can
            easily consume sufficient vegetable food for all purposes
            of life and helth; whereas for persons who lead
            sedentary lives, a smaller bulk of more concentrated
            food will probably be found more beneficial.</p>
            <p>   The combination of eggs, milk, butter, and cheese,
            with vegetables, makes a dietary that is quite sufficient
            for life and health; and it is questionable whether it
            is not really the best sort of food for all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter" xml:id="soups">
            <head type="main">HOUSEHOLD COOKERY.</head>
            <head type="sub">SOUPS.</head>
            <p>SOUP may be made of meat, vegetables, bones, milk,
            fish, etc., and is liquid food of a warming and very
            nourishing kind. Our bodies require a certain amount
            of liquid, and soup supplies that want in an excellent
            and healthful manner. Warm food is much more
            nourishing than cold. As the stomach requires
            quantity as well as quality to assist digestion, and as
            it can contain a great deal more than is necessary, it
            is desirable to decrease the appetite for solid food.
            The French use the liquid in which fish, vegetables,
            and meat of all kinds have been boiled to make light,
            nourishing soups. It is advisable to make soup a
            daily article of food; and for that purpose meat is
            not always necessary. Vegetables, beans, peas, lentils,
            tomatoes, etc., make excellent soups, in which the
            want of meat is difficult to discover.</p>
            <p>   Warm light soup is excellent for invalids or persons
            afflicted with sleeplessness, as the warm liquid enters
            the blood quickly, and draws it away from the head
            in order to assist the stomach to perform its functions,
            thereby causing drowsiness.</p>
            <p>   Beans, peas, and lentils are all nitrogenous vegetable
            foods; and, when used in the composition of soup,
            supply almost entirely the want of meat.</p>
            <p>   Tomatoes are much used and highly prized, especially
            in soups; they are powerful purifiers of the blood and
            highly nutritious. A celebrated medical man describes
            the tomato as "an invaluable article of diet," and
            ascribes to it various important medical properties.
            "It is an almost sovereign remedy for dyspepsia and
            indigestion, and is the most healthy article of diet
            now in use."</p>
            <p>   Tinned tomatoes can be procured at a cheap rate
            and very good; they can be used where fresh tomatoes
            are not procurable.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Haricot Bean Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Beans.</item>
                        <item>2 oz. of Fat Bacon, or 1 small
                        table-spoonful of Butter or
                        Dripping.</item>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Small piece of Celery.</item>
                        <item>2 breakfast-cupfuls Milk.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Wash the beans, and soak them for a day and night
            in cold water. Put them into a pot with 2 quarts of
            water and a piece of fat pork, or a small table-spoonful
            of butter or dripping. Let it all boil; then add the
            vegetables, cleaned and roughly cut up; a little car-
            bonate of soda, the size of a pea, may be added, as
            sometimes the beans are old and very hard. Let all
            boil for <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> hours, then put it thorugh a strainer; it
            must be well mashed up, and use some of the milk to
            wash it through, as all ought to be put through, except
            the skins of the beans. Now add the milk; pepper
            and salt to taste. Warm all up in the pot, and serve.</p>
            <p>   <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—No salt must be put in until the beans are
            quite boiled, as salt hardens them and renders them
            difficult to boil down.</p>
            <p>   Half of a can of tomatoes boiled with the beans
            for the last half hour, and all rubbed through the
            strainer, makes a delightful change in this soup, and
            adds greatly to its valuable properties. The milk is
            left out when tomatoes are used.</p>
            <p>   Beans have much the same component parts as
            cheese, and are almost as strengthening in every
            respect as beef. Their only want is fat, but the bacon
            or butter supplies that.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Cottage Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Neck of Mutton.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of Rice.</item>
                        <item>1 Carrot.</item>
                        <item>1 Turnip.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> quarts of Water.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 large Leeks.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful Dripping.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful Sugar.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put into a dry, clean pot a table-spoonful of sweet
            dripping, or fat of some kind; let it get quite hot.
            Cut up the mutton into small square pieces; put
            it and the bones into the pot with the fat, and fry
            them, turning them over and over with a spoon.</p>
            <p>   Cut up the carrot and turnip into small square
            pieces like the size of peas, and add them to the meat;
            then the leeks, washed and cut small; keep turning
            all over with the spoon; then add the rice, well
            washed, a teaspoonful of sugar, and a teaspoonful of
            salt. Let the whole be turned about in the pot with
            the spoon for more than <num>5</num> minutes; then add <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num>
            quarts of water. Put on the lid, bring it to the boil,
            and boil slowly rather over an hour. Add pepper and
            salt, and it is ready.</p>
            <p>   <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—There are <num>4</num> breakfast-cupfuls in a quart.</p>
            <p>   This is an excellent vegetable soup, and a very
            valuable article of food from the vegetables it contains.
            The fat supplies a want in the vegtables. This soup
            is extremely good made without any meat, and the
            small quantity of sugar counteracts any disagreeable
            effects leeks or onions may have on the stomach.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Lentil Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Lentils.</item>
                        <item>Carrot, Turnip, Parsnip.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Onions or Leeks.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Take <num>1</num> lb. of lentils and wash them thoroughly in
            many waters until they are perfectly clean; soak
            them for a night in cold water; then put them into
            a pot with the water in which they are soaked and
            as much more as makes <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> quarts, or <num>10</num> breakfast-
            cupfuls. When this boilds, add carrot, turnip, parsnip,
            <num>2</num> large onion, all cut up roughly, and a small pinch
            of carbonate of soda about the size of a pea. Allow
            it to boil <num>2</num> hours, then strain through a cullender,
            washing the lentils all through except the skins;
            return it to the pot to warm. Season with pepper
            and salt, and serve.</p>
            <p>   Lentil soup is delightful if nicely made, and requires
            no meat of any kind, or bones, as it has the taste
            and the good properties of butcher meat to a large
            extent in itself.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Windsor Milk Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Potatoes.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> a Turnip.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num>a Parsnip.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                        <item>1 oz. Butter.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Small bit of Celery (if possible).</item>
                        <item>2 large Leeks or Onions.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful of Sugar,
                        Flour, or Sago.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put into a pot the potatoes, turnip, parsnip, celery,
            onions, or leeks, all cut up in small pieces; then add
            the sugar and putter; put it on the fire to get quite
            hot—add <num>2</num> quarts of water, and boil for an hour
            till all the vegetables are soft. Put through a strainer,
            using a spoon to press it through, and return it to
            the pot with a table-spoonful of flour that has been
            moistened in a breakfast-cupful milk, and boil for
            <num>5</num> minutes, sitrring frequently till it boils. Two
            table-spoonfuls of sago may be used instead of the
            flour; it should be washed and moistened in the same
            way as the flour, and stirred till it boils. Add salt
            and pepper to taste, and serve.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>German Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Neck of Mutton.</item>
                        <item>4 Potatoes.</item>
                        <item>2 good-sized Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 large red Carrot.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Rice.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put the mutton, well washed, into a pot with <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num>
            quarts of water; when it boils, add the onions chopped
            up finely, the potatoes peeled and cut in very small
            pieces, and the carrot grated; add a teaspoonful of salt,
            and let the whole boil <num>2</num> hours. Then was a teacupful
            of rice (which is <num type="fraction">1/4</num> of a lb.) and add it, and allow the
            whole to boil half-an-hour longer. Season with enough
            pepper and salt, and the soup is ready.</p>
            <p>   This is a delightful soup, and very cheap.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Skirt Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> lbs. Beef Skirt</item>
                        <item>1 large Carrot.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Remove all skin from the beef skirt and the fat;
            cut it up in pieces about half-an-inch suqare, and put
            the meat on in a pot with <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> quarts of cold water.
            Scrape and wash the carrot, peel the turnip, and cut
            both up in small square pieces about the size of peas;
            add them when the pot boils. Add also half a tea-
            spoonful of salt, and boil the whole for <num>2</num> hours.
            Season with pepper and salt to taste.</p>
            <p>   This soup is delightful, and contains as much
            nourishment as good beef-tea. Beef skirt contains a
            considerable amount of good gravy, and is a part of
            the animal which lies just within the ribs.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Green Pea Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 peck of Peas.</item>
                        <item>Stock Parsley.</item>
                        <item>Mint.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Onion.</item>
                        <item>Sugar.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Shell the pease, which should be young; put the
            shells into a stewpan with a quart of water, a teaspoon-
            ful of salt, and <num>1</num> of sugar; boil for <num>1</num> hour, then pulp
            thorugh a cullender or sieve; return to the pot, and
            add <num>1</num> quart of good stock, made with shin of beef;
            add <num>1</num> onion and a few leaves of lettuce, chopeed very
            finely, a very little parsley, mint, and the pease; boil
            till the vegetables are tender (about <num>15</num> minutes);
            then season to taste, and serve.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Mutton Broth.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Neck of Mutton.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Barley.</item>
                        <item>1 large Carrot.</item>
                        <item>1 small Turnip.</item>
                        <item>1 small Cabbage or Savoy.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 large Leeks.</item>
                        <item>A little Parsley.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3 1/2</num> quarts Water.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put the barley, mutton, and water into the pot; let
            them boil half-an-hour; then add the carrot, turnip,
            cabbage, and leeks, cut up <hi rend="italic">very</hi> finely, with <num>1</num> teaspoon-
            ful of salt. Let all boil for an hour-and-a-half; add
            the parsley chopped up finely, and enough salt and
            pepper to season; then serve.</p>
            <p>   <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—Barley should be washed, and vegetables cut
            and left in water till they are required.</p>
            <p>   To make the vegetables for this soup more delicate
            and digestible, cut them all up as indicated above, put
            them in a basin, and cover them with boiling water.
            When they stand thus for <num>10</num> minutes, the water may
            be drained, and the vegetables put into the pot and
            boiled as above.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Potato Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Neck of Mutton.</item>
                        <item>2 lbs. Potatoes.</item>
                        <item>3 onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Carrot.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   This soup is excellent made with bones, either raw
            or cooked; with any inferior piece of beef or mutton;
            with liquor in which tripe has been boiled; or with
            part of a pluck. If made from raw bones, they must
            be boiled for several hours before the potatoes are
            put in.</p>
            <p>   Take the mutton and put it in a pot with three
            quarts of cold water; bring to the boil; pare thinly
            and slice small <num>2</num> lbs. potatoes, and add them to the
            soup when it boils. Grate a nice red carrot, chop
            up the onions very finely, and add all to the soup,
            with a little pepper and salt. Boil <num>2</num> hours,
            season to taste, and serve. The potatoes should be
            boiled to a pulp, and the soup be nice and thick,
            not watery.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Carrot Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>6 Carrots.</item>
                        <item>1 Turnip.</item>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Celery.</item>
                        <item>Stock.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   This soup may be made of second stock, or of bones
            of roast beef or mutton. Put <num>2</num> quarts of stock in a
            stewpan, with <num>6</num> carrots, <num>1</num> small turnip, <num>2</num> onions; a
            blade of celery is an improvement. The carrots must
            either be grated or cut in very small pieces. Add a
            table-spoonful of flour, wet in a little water; allow the
            whole to boil for <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> hours, until the carrots are tender;
            pass the soup through a wire sieve or cullender; rub
            the carrot through; return to the pot to warm, and
            add salt and pepper.</p>
            <p>   If made with raw bones, the stock is much better
            boiled the day previous, as the fat can be taken off
            when the soup is cold.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Rice Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 quarts Stock.</item>
                        <item>4 large Leeks.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of whole Rice.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Milk.</item>
                        <item>Parsley.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put into a pot <num>2</num> quarts of liquor in which a fowl or
            a knuckle of veal has been boiled. It may be improved
            by having a carrot and small turnip boiled along with
            it, which can be picked out at the last. Now add
            to the soup the white part of the leeks cut up
            in very thin pieces, and the rice well washed, and
            boil for half-an-hour; then add a table-spoonful of
            parsley washed, dried, and chopped up very finely,
            a breakfast-cupful of good milk, and salt and pepper.
            After boiling for <num>5</num> minutes, the soup will be ready.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Stock from Bones.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>6 lbs. Bones.</item>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                        <item>1 Carrot.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Peppercorns.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Raw and cooked bones should not be boiled together.</p>
            <p>   Take <num>6</num> lbs. of raw bones; remove as much marrow
            and fat from them as possible; put them in a pot and
            cover them well with cold water (see that the bones
            are all covered, as any portion remaining uncovered
            adds no strength to the soup); add <num>2</num> onions, <num>1</num> large
            carrot, <num>1</num> turnip, a teaspoonful of peppercorns, and boil <num>8</num>
            hours on a slow fire. Care must be taken that the water
            does not reduce too much; in that case it must be
            added to. The stock is best to simmer very slowly by
            the fire all day, and then be strained through a sieve.
            The next day the fat may be removed, and the stock
            is ready for use.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Fisherman's Rice Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> lbs. of Fish.</item>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>Bit of Celery of Carrot.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. of Rice.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> quarts of Water.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Handful of Parsley.</item>
                        <item>2 Tomatoes or 1 cupful of
                        Tinned Tomato.</item>
                        <item>A blade of Mace.</item>
                        <item>6 Cloves.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put on the water in the soup-pot to boil; have the
            fish cleansed thoroughly and cut up in pieces; put it
            in; add the onion, carrot, turnip, the mace and cloves,
            and the celery. Let all boil <num>1</num> hour and strain. Have
            the pot washed out and put the stock back into it.
            Skin the tomatoes, and cut them up and add them.
            Wash the rice and add it, and let it all boil for <num>20</num>
            minutes longer. Add salt and pepper to season well.</p>
            <p>   Trimmings of fish make this soup very well, or
            small fish of different kinds, such as children catch.</p>
            <p>   A few oysters or other shell-fish may be added at
            the last, but must not boil; only thoroughly heat.</p>
            <p>   Tomato is skinned easily if it be dipped in boiling
            water for one moment.</p>
            <p>   This soup is delightful.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Tomato Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Small table-spoonful Butter
                        or Fat.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> a tin of Tomatoes, or 1 lb.
                        Tomatoes.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                        <item>3 table-spoonfuls Tapioca.</item>
                        <item>2 quarts Stock.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put into a flat stew-pan an ounce of butter, or some
            fat ham cut in small pieces (there should be a table-
            spoonful). When it is hot, put in <num>2</num> middle-sized
            onions sliced, and fry them; then add half a tin
            of tomatoes, or <num>1</num> lb. of fresh tomatoes, cut up roughly
            in pieces. Let this all stew for about <num>20</num> minutes,
            after which rub it through a sieve or cullender to
            keep back the seeds and to pulp the tomatoes and
            onions. Have <num>2</num> quarts of common stock made either
            with a small piece of mutton, veal, or beef; it need
            not be rich, as the very plainest is quite good for
            this soup. Add the pulp of the tomatoes, etc., to
            the stock, and set it on the fire to boil; then put
            in <num>3</num> table-spoonfuls of tapioca which has been soaked
            for an hour in either warm or cold water, and keep
            stirring till it boils. The soup will be ready after
            boiling for <num>10</num> minutes, and having pepper and salt
            added to it.</p>
            <p>   <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—If fresh tomatoes are used, half a cupful
            of water may be put in along with them.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Chicken Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Fowl.</item>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>Small bit of Turnip.</item>
                        <item>A dessert-spoonful of Chopped
                        Parsley.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> quarts of Water.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Blade of Celery.</item>
                        <item>Bit of Mace and 4 Cloves.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Arrowroot.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of good Milk or
                        Cream.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Empty, cleanse, and truss the fowl; put the water
            in the soup-pot, and when it is hot put in the fowl.
            When it boils add the vegetables all cut up, and boil
            from <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> to <num>2</num> hours. Remove the fowl, and strain the
            stock through a very fine strainer or napkin. Have
            the pot thoroughly washed, and return the stock to it.
            Then mix the arrowroot and the milk together, add
            salt and pepper, and put it all in the stock. Stir till
            it boils; then add the parsley, and boil for <num>1</num> or <num>2</num>
            minutes longer. If this soup is made with an old fowl,
            it may require to boil <num>2</num> hours; if a chicken, <num>1</num> hour or
            <num type="fraction"> 1 1/2</num> hours will be sufficient.</p>
            <p>   Serve the fowl with white sauce over it.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Kidney Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Shin of Beef</item>
                        <item>1 Ox Kidney.</item>
                        <item>1 oz Butter.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Carrot, 1 Turnip.</item>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                        <item>2 table-spoonfuls Corn-flour.</item>
                        <item>Pepper, Salt, Mustard, Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   To make stock for kidney soup, take all the marrow
            from the shin of beef and put it into a soup-pot
            with <num>2</num> quarts of water. Bring it to the boil. Add
            the carrot, tunip, and onions, cut up into pieces,
            and allow all to boil at least <num>3</num> hours, when it must
            be strained. Take a fresh ox kidney, wash it well,
            and dry it. Remove all the fat from the middle,
            and cut up the kidney into half-inch pieces. Put
            the butter in a stew-pan and let it get quite brown,
            but not burnt; then put inn the pieces of kidney
            and fry them all round. When quite fried, stir
            in a table-spoonful of flour and mix it well till the
            flour has absorbed all the moisture in the pan, then
            add a teaspoonful of salt, half a teaspoonful each of
            pepper, dry mustard, and sugar, stirring till they
            become a paste in the pan. Now add <num>2</num> breakfast-
            cupfuls of water, and stir over the fire till it boils.
            Set it on a slow part of the fire, and allow it all
            to boil for at least <num>2</num> hours, stirring frequently,
            Return the strained stock to the pot, and add the
            kidney to it. Mix in a basin the corn-flour and a
            little water, and pour this also into the pot with enough
            of salt to season the whole, stirring occasionally
            till it boils, when the soup is ready.</p>
            <p>   This soup, if well made, requires no artificial brown-
            ing; it may be made still browner by leaving the
            skins on the onions, which must be well washed.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Onion Soup.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Small Knuckle of Veal</item>
                        <item>6 large Onions.</item>
                        <item>1 small Turnip.</item>
                        <item>1 Parsnip.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Piece of Celery.</item>
                        <item>Blade of Mace.</item>
                        <item>Salt, Pepper, and Sugar.</item>
                        <item>Flour, Butter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put the knuckle of veal on to boil with <num>2</num> quarts
            of cold water, allowing it to boil an hour. Peel and
            cut up the onions, and soak them for an hour in cold
            water; also cut up into small pieces the turnip,
            parsnip, and celery, and add them to the soup, along
            with the mace, a teaspoonful of salt, half a teaspoonful
            of pepper, and half a teaspoonful of sugar. Let all
            boil <num>2</num> hours and strain, rubbing the onions through
            the strainer; then return the soup to the pot, and
            add a small table-spoonful of butter and <num>2</num> table-spoon-
            fuls of flour mixed together, and a breakfast-cupful
            of milk—stirring it till it boils. Allow it to boil
            <num>5</num> minutes, when the soup is ready; after which
            season to taste.</p>
            <p>   This soup is made frequently without meat, leaving
            out the veal, and making it in every other respect
            the same.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Hotch-Potch.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>3 lbs. Neck of Mutton or Lamb.</item>
                        <item>6 young Turnips.</item>
                        <item>6 young Carrots.</item>
                        <item>6 young Onions.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> quarts of Water.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Lettuce.</item>
                        <item>1 Cauliflower.</item>
                        <item>2 pints of Green Peas.</item>
                        <item>1 handful of Parsley.</item>
                        <item>Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>   Put rather more than half of the mutton or lamb
            in the soup-pot, with the water and a little salt; when
            it boils, skim it carefully, and allow it to boil for
            an hour.</p>
            <p>   Cut up the remainder of the mutton or lamb
            into small chops and add them; also the turnips
            and carrots; cut up in neat square pieces the onions
            and half of the peas, and allow it to boil for half-an-
            hour longer. Chop up the lettuce, divide the cauli-
            flower into sprigs, chop the parsley finely, and add all
            to the soup, with the remainder of the peas, and boil
            for another half hour, when season to taste and serve.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter" xml:id="fish">
            <head>FISH.</head>
            <p>THE varieties of fish available for food in this country
            are numerous and excellent; those containing the
            least fat are the most easily digested. The flesh
            of fish contains fibrine, gelatine, and albumen in
            small proportions, mineral matter and water in
            larger.</p>
            <p>   Whitting, haddock, and soles are nearly equally
            digestible, and even suitable for the food of invalids.
            Salmon, mackerel, and herring are more oily, and
            not quite so digestible. The common herring con-
            tains a large amount of nourishment, and if cooked
            so as to get rid of some of its superabundant oil,
            cointains a large amount of nourishment at a cheap
            rate. Lobsters and crabs are not easily digested,
            and to some people are injurious. They are rather
            coars feeders, and this may, to some extent, account
            for their indigestibility. All fish <hi rend="italic">out of season</hi> are
            unwholesome, and sometimes positively injurious.
            Buckland, who has given so much information on
            the nature and habits of fish, writes very emphati-
            cally against the taking and using of fish out of
            season.</p>
            <p>   It is said that fish are fully as nutritious as animal
            food; and though they may not have such a satisfying
            effect upon the stomach, that arises from their being
            so easily digested. They are n ot only good food,
            but food of the best description, well able to supply
            the wants of the body, suitable for young and old,
            healthy people and invalids.</p>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>To Fry Fish, Etc.</head>
               <p>   All fish are fried in a somewhat similar manner, and
               a few general directions may be given.</p>
               <p>   Fish that are to be fried should be made perfectly
               dry, and, to accomplish this, must be covered either
               with flour or bread-crumbs. The fat should be perfectly
               hot, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, at the temperature of at least <num>345°</num> Fahr. This
               is ascertained in several ways. The best is to use a
               thermometer; but as that is not always to be had, a
               very good way is to put the fat on the fire and allow
               it to get hot till it begins to smoke. It must be quite
               still, for as long as fat bubbles there is water in it.
               When the fat becomes quite still, and <hi rend="italic">slightly smokes</hi>,
               put the fish in and fry till they become a light brown.
               Another good rule is to have plenty of fat to cover
               whatever you wish to fry. After the fish are fried,
               put them on a cloth or coarse paper before the fire to
               drain. Those rules of the heat of fat refer to all kinds
               of frying, fritters, etc.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <list>
                           <item>3 Small Whittings or
                           Haddocks.</item>
                           <item>Bread-crumbs.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>Egg.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                           <item>Lard or Dripping.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Have nice fresh haddocks or whitings; wash and
               fry them well, and rub them with a little flour in which
               is mixed some pepper and salt; beat up an egg on a
               plate, cover the fish well with it, and roll them in dry
               bread-crumbs. Prepare the fat for frying as directed
               above, and put the fish in, not many at a time, as the
               temperature of the fat must not be reduced too much.
               A few minutes is enough to fry the fish if the fat quite
               covers them; if it does not, turn them over and fry
               them on the other side. They ought to be of a nice
               brown colour; and if proper attention is paid to the
               heat of the fat, the fish will be perfectly whole. They
               are equally well fried without the egg and bread-
               crumbs, using only flour to dry them, but they do not
               look quite so well. A slice of a large fish, or fillets of
               fish, should all be fried in the same way. Melted butter
               may be served with them. Haddocks are the better of
               being skinned; but the skin of whiting is very delicate,
               and does not require to be removed</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Fish Puddding.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 lb. Fish.</item>
                           <item>Potatoes.</item>
                           <item>1 oz. Butter.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Egg.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Take any remains of boiled fish; carefully remove
               the flesh from the bones, and cut it up into small dice,
               and have equal bulk of mashed potatoes. Put both
               into a basin and mix them together with a fork, then
               melt the butter and pour it in, mixing well; add salt
               and pepper and a few grains of cayenne pepper; beat
               up an egg and add it last; mix all well together; put
               it in a pudding-dish, smooth and score it neatly at the
               top, and bake for half-an-hour.</p>
               <p>   The same mixture is very good made into small round
               cakes. Flour them well outside. Put a table-spoonful
               of dripping in a frying pan to get quite hot; put in a
               few cakes at a time to fry a brown colour on both sides.
               Then drain and serve. They are a breakfast dish.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Boiled Haddock or Cod.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>3 lbs. Cod</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Procure a piece of cod weighing <num>3</num> lbs., or a haddock
               of similar weight; scrape very clean, and, if quite fresh,
               an hour or two in salt is an improvement. Have a fish-
               kettle containing plenty of boiling water, well flavoured
               with salt; put the fish in and boil for a minute, then
               pour in a cupful of cold water, gently, to reduce the heat,
               and allow the fish to cook in the water, below boiling
               heat, for about <num>15</num> or <num>20</num> minutes, according to the
               thickness of the fish; it must be immediately taken
               out and drained, as to allow fish to remain in water
               after it is boiled spoils it; dish it on napkin with some
               parsley to garnish, and serve with melted butter in a
               sauceboat, separately.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Baked Haddock.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Haddock.</item>
                           <item>Bread-crumbs.</item>
                           <item>Parsley.</item>
                           <item>Herbs.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>Suet.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                           <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Procure a fine fresh haddock of <num>2</num> lbs. weight; wash
               and scrape it quite clean; take out the eyes and dry it
               outside and inside, then prepare the following stuffing:—
               A teacupful of bread-crumbs, <num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. of suet or butter,
               a dessert-spoonful of chopped parsley, a teaspoonful
               of chopped herbs, pepper and salt; either an egg or
               a little milke moistens this. Form the stuffing like a 
               sausage, place it in the belly of the fish, and sew it up;
               truss the haddock into the form of the letter S, brush
               the top over with a little beaten egg, sprinkle bread-
               crumbs over, and put it in the oven to bake for
               half-an-hour. It must be frequently basted with fresh
               dripping while baking. Serve with melted butter.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>To Stew Fish.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> lbs. Fish.</item>
                           <item>1 Onion.</item>
                           <item>Vinegar.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>Flour.</item>
                           <item>1 oz. Butter or Dripping.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Any of the coarser kinds of fish do well to stew; and
               the different varieties of fish stews have always been
               favourite dishes where fish are easily procured.</p>
               <p>   Cut up the fish into pieces about <num>2</num> inches long, after
               being well washed and cleaned. Put the dripping or
               butter into a small stew-pan, and let it get quite hot;
               chop up the onion and fry it brown in the hot fat;
               sprinkle a dessert-spoonful of flour into the pan, and
               stir it smooth; then add a teaspoonful of vinegar, salt
               and pepper to taste, and a breakfast-cupful of water.
               Stir till it boils; then put in the pieces of fish, put on the
               lid, and let them simmer very gently for <num>10</num> minutes.
               Skate (which stews very well) takes <num>20</num> minutes, or
               even longer; but, in general, <num>10</num> minutes is quite enough
               time. Serve with the sauce over the fish.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Salt Fish, to Cook.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 lb. Salt Ling or Cod.</item>
                           <item>Flour. Milk.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 oz. Butter.</item>
                           <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Salted fish are neither so nutritious nor so profitable
               as fresh fish; because salt extracts the juices from the
               fish, and greatly wastes it nourishing properties.</p>
               <p>   Cut up the fish into convenient pieces and soak it all
               night in cold water. Either scrape the skin till it is
               white, or putt it off altogether. Put the fish on in a
               stew-pan, covered with cold water, to boil for three-
               quarters of an hour, or longer if very hard; take it
               up on a dish and drain the water entirely from it,
               wiping the dish quite dry. Boil the egg hard, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, for
               10 minutes; take off the shell and chop it up. Take
               a small sauce-pan and put inn it an ounce of butter and
               a dessert-spoonful of flour, stirring them together over
               the fire; then add a breakfast-cupful of milk, and stir
               till it boils; add the chopped up egg, and mix. Pour
               the whole over the fish, and serve.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Salt Fish Pie.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Potatoes.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Fish.</item>
                           <item>Parsley.</item>
                           <item>Onion.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>Mustard.</item>
                           <item>Vinegar.</item>
                           <item>Pepper.</item>
                           <item>Dripping.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Boil about <num>9</num> potatoes, and mash them quite smoothly,
               adding a very little milk to moisten them. Have the
               fish boiled (the remains of fish previously cooked will
               do). Put into a small pudding-dish <num>3</num> spoonfuls of the
               mashed potatoes, and spread it over the bottom of the
               dish; then put in the fish, broken up with a fork into
               flakes; over that sprinkle a table-spoonful of finely-
               chopped parsley, and a small cooked onion chopped up.
               Then add half a teaspoonful of mustard, made with
               vinegar instead of water, and a few small bits of
               dripping or butter, and cover all with the remainder
               of the mashed potatoes, making the top smooth, and
               marking it neatly. Put the pie into an oven for three-
               quarters of an hour, or on a toaster in front of the fire,
               to brown the potatoes nicely.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Baked Herrings.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>6 fresh Herrings.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Salt.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Pepper.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/3</num> teacupful Vinegar.</item>
                           <item>1 Bay Leaf.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teacupful Water.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>   Fresh herrings should not be washed, unless in
               exceptional circumstances. They should be emptied,
               the heads taken off, the scales scraped off, and then the
               herrings well wiped. With a sharp knife split the
               herring up the back and lay it open; cut it in half;
               lift the bone out, beginning at the head; now roll each
               half up into a nice firm roll, beginning at the head;
               from <num>6</num> herrings you will have <num>12</num> of these rolls.</p>
               <p>   Stand them in a small pudding dish with the back
               uppermost—they will quite fill the dish. Now pour
               in half a teacupful of water and one-third of a teacupful
               of vinegar mixed, a bay leaf slipped in at the side, and
               the pepper and salt. Cover the dish over with a plate,
               and cook at the side of the fire, or in the over, for half-
               an-hour. The herrings may be served in the dish in
               which they are cooked. They are good either hot or cold</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>Fried Fresh Herrings.</head>
               <p>   Prepare as above—namely, empty the herrings, take
               off the heads, scrape the scales off, and wipe them quite
               clean; then split them open from the back and lay them
               flat. Dust over them a little pepper and salt.</p>
               <p>   Have a clean frying-pan quite hot; place the herrings
               in it, the skin next the pan, and fry them for <num>5</num> minutes;
               then fry the other side about the same time. Fry the
               skin side first. Good herrings need no dripping, as
               they contain sufficient oil in themselves to fry in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>Salmon, to Boil.</head>
               <p>   Empty the salmon and wash it, but handle the fish
               as little as possible, to prevent the scales from being
               rubbed off. Put into a fish-kettle enoguh water
               to cover the fish with salt in the proportion of a table-
               spoonful to each gallon of water. When it boils, put
               the fish in, and let it boil for <num>5</num> minutes; then put
               <num>2</num> breakfast-cupfuls of cold water in to reduce the
               temperature, and put the kettle on a cooler part of the
               fire; allow it to remain thus under boiling point for
               the proper time; then take the fish-kettle off the fire
               and allow it to stand for <num>10</num> minutes before removing
               the salmon. This improves the flavour and makes
               the fish firmer.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>A table of time to boil salmon</head>
                  <item><seg xml:id="aslice">A slice weighing</seg> 1 lb. <seg xml:id="requires">requires</seg> a quarter of an hour.</item>
                  <item><seg copyOf="#aslice">"</seg> 3 lbs. <seg copyOf="#requires">"</seg> 25 minutes.</item>
                  <item>6 lbs. from a thick fish <seg copyOf="#requires"></seg> 40 minutes.</item>
                  <item>A grilse weighing about 7 or 8 lbs., half-an-hour.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="chapter" xml:id="meat">
            <head>MEAT.</head>
            <head>To Stew and Roast.</head>
            <p>FOR the cooking of all meat which is not to be made
            into soup, but either stewed, roasted, or broiled, one
            rule, without exception, applies—namely, that the out-
            side of the meat be quickly subjected to strong heat,
            in order to shut up all the pores, after which a slower
            porcess of cooking should be proceeded with, such
            as suits each particular kind of meat.</p>
            <p>   To stew meat is the most profitable of those three
            methods of cooking, as no part of the meast is lost, and
            there is, besides, a good gravy which supllements it.</p>
            <p>   The principle of all stewing, whether applied to
            beef, mutton, chicken, or game, is, first of all, to put
            into a pot some kind of fat (either butter, suet, or
            dripping) and make it <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> hot; then put in the
            piece of meat, small or large, and fry it all roun
            to shut the pores; then put in less or more water or
            other liquid, and stew the meat for the given time.
            This rule applies alike to small pieces of steak or large
            joints. The reason is, that the heat hardens the
            albumen in the meat all over the surface, and stops
            up the pores like sealing-wax on bottles; the juice
            is thus kept in, so that the meat cooked is much more
            savoury.</p>
            <p>Roasting is a more wasteful way of cooking; but
            roasted meat, if well cooked, is more easily digested.
            A roast should be put very near a hot fire for <num>5</num>
            minutes to shut up the pores, and afterwards put
            a good deal further back, and cooked more slowly.
            The secret of having meat well roasted is to have an
            even heat, and to baste it very frequently. Basting
            keeps the meat from drying up, and the action of the
            fire on the hot fat with which it is basted keeps
            the surface of the meat well crusted over, and all the
            juice retained in the joint.</p>
            <p>Broiling or grilling is really just roasting a small
            slice of meat instead of a large piece. It certainly
            is not a very economical mode of cooking, but, if well
            done and not over-cooked, is very easily digested and
            nourishing. The principle is exactly the same as
            roasting:—Let the meat be put on a hot gridiron
            over a clear hot fire for a minute or two to shut up
            the pores, turning both sides to the fire; afterwards
            a little slower, to cook it to the heart. Eight or ten
            minutes is enough to grill steak nearly an inch thick;
            of course a little depends upon the fire, but no grilling
            is well executed unless the fire is clear and quite free
            from smoke. Both roasted and broiled meat are
            <hi rend="italic">spoiled</hi> if over-done. Broiled meat should be turned
            very often, and thus bastes itself, just as roasted meat
            requires to be basted.</p>
            <p>Frying and frying-pans have been very much
            abused of late years; and one heard of "dirty frying-
            pans and greasy messes," but there is no need for the
            frying-pan to be dirty, or the food greasy, and for
            certain kinds of flesh and fish frying is a very good
            mode of cooking. Almost without exception, the rule
            above applied to roasting or stewing applies to frying.
            The meat to be fried should be put either on a hot pan
            to shut up the pores, or in hot fat for the same purpose.
            This has always the effect of retaining the juices in
            the meat, and consequently making it more tender.
            The more juices belonging to fish, flesh, or fowl
            are bottled up, the more tender and digestible the
            meat will be. Flesh that is fried should not be over-
            cooked, as in that case it gets dry and indigestible.</p>
            <p>Pork takes a longer time, either to roast or fry, than
            other flesh; and it should always be well cooked, as
            when underdone it is very disagreeable and unwhole-
            some. White flesh of all kinds, either of animals or
            fowls, takes a lot longer time than brown, and requires
            to be more thoroughly cooked.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Ox-tail Stewed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Ox-tail.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Ketchup.</item>
                        <item>Dripping.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>Carrot and Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the tail well in warm water, and cut it up at
            the jointes; the larger joints may be cut in two. Dry
            the pieces well, and mix on a plate a table-spoonful of
            flour, a teaspoonful of salt, and half a teaspoonful of
            pepper. Rub each piece of tail over with this
            mixture. Put into a stew-pan a table-spoonful of
            dripping, and let it get quite hot; then fry the pieces
            of tail all round in it, and lift them out when done.
            Pour out the fat that remains, and return the pieces
            of tail to the pan with the onion chopped up, <num>2</num> break-
            fast-cupfuls of water, and the ketchup, and stew
            gently for an hour-and-a-half. Cut the carrot and
            turnip into very neat pieces, add them, and stew three-
            quarters of an hour longer.</p>
            <p>If well and slowly cooked, this is a delightful stew,
            as the ox-tail contains a great deal of gelatine.</p>
            <p>Dish the meat in the centre of a dish with the
            vegetables round it. Take the fat from the gravy
            and strain it over all.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Rabbit Stewed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Rabbit.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Butter or Dripping.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the rabbit well and dry it thoroughly outside
            and inside; then cut it up into joints, after taking off
            the head and removing the heart and liver. In order
            to dry it still better, rub over each piece with flour.
            Put into a stew-pan a dessert-spoonful of butter or
            dripping; let it get quite hot; then put in the pieces
            of rabbit and fry them. When all are fried, add a 
            breakfast-cupful of water, an onion finely chopped up,
            and the heart and liver. Take out the eyes, and wash
            the head well; add it also, and stew the whole slowly
            with the lid closely on for an hour, stirring it
            occasionally. Dish neatly, and pour the sauce over.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Ox Kidney Stewed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Ox Kidney.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful Flour.</item>
                        <item>Mustard.</item>
                        <item>Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Butter.</item>
                        <item>Ketchup.</item>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash an ox kidney well and dry it thoroughly;
            then cut it up into thin slices, after all the fat has
            been removed from the middle. Put into a small
            stew-pan a dessert-spoonful of butter; let it get quite
            hot and quite brown; chop up the onion and fry it
            slightly; then put in the pieces of kidney and fry them
            well. Sprinkle in gradually the flour, and stir till it
            is quite mixed with the moisture in the pan. Add,
            now, a teaspoonful of salt, half a teaspoonful each of
            pepper, dry mustard, and sugar; a table-spoonful of
            ketchup may be added. Stir all well over the fire till
            it be quite dry, like a paste. Now add a breakfast-
            cupful and a half of water, and stir till it boils up;
            put on the lid, and allow it to stew <hi rend="italic">very</hi> gently for an
            hour-and-a-half. Serve with nicely-shaped pieces of
            toasted bread round. The kidney may be cut up in
            only 6 or 8 thick pieces or left whole. In those cases
            it must cook longer.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Steak Stuffed and Rolled.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Steak.</item>
                        <item>2 breakfast-cupfuls of
                        Grated Bread.</item>
                        <item>2 table-spoonfuls Suet,
                        chopped.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful Parsley,
                        chopped.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful Salt.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Pepper.</item>
                        <item>Dripping.</item>
                        <item>Carrot and Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Get 2 thin slices of steak, cut from the top of the
            rump, weighing half a pound each, and about a quarter
            of an inch in thickness. Put the grated bread, the
            suet, the parsley, pepper, and salt into a bowl, and
            mix them well. Beat up the egg well, and stir it in
            among the bread-crumps, etc., in the basin; with the
            hand knead it to wet the whole mixture, and gather
            it into a lump; but if the egg is not enough to moisten
            the mixture, add a very little milk or water. Divide
            the stuffing into 2 pieces, and shape them like a
            turkey's egg; roll this neatly into each piece of steak
            and tie it up with string. Each piece should be very
            neatly shaped.</p>
            <p>Put into a stew-pan a dessert-spoonful of nice drip-
            ping, and when it has got quite hot, fry the pieces of
            meat in it. Pour off any dripping that remains, and
            put into the pan a cupful and a half of water, and
            allow it to stew for a quarter of an hour; then add
            2 onions, and a pretty large carrot cut in quarters
            lengthways, and a little salt, and stew for an hour.</p>
            <p>Take off the string from the steak, and place it on a 
            dish; arrange the vegetables neatly round, and strain
            the sauce over.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Dutch Stew.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> lbs. Neck of Mutton.</item>
                        <item>1 small, firm Cabbage.</item>
                        <item>6 Potatoes.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> table-spoonful Dripping.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Put into a pot the dripping, and let it get hot; then
            slice the onions, and fry them gently in it. Wash the
            mutton well, and put it in the pot with the clean
            water that hangs about it. Put the lid instantly and
            closely on the pot, and let it stew slowly for three-
            quarters of an hour.</p>
            <p>Take a nice, firm cabbage, wash it, remove the
            withered leaves, and cut it into 8 pieces length-
            ways, like the divisions of an orange; place the
            cabbage in water; peel 6 potatoes and cut them in
            slices half an inch thick, and place them also in the
            water. When the meat has stewed for three-quarters
            of an hour, lift the cabbage, dripping with water, and
            the potatoes, and pack both round the meat; sprinkle
            over them a teaspoonful of salt and haf a teaspoon-
            ful of pepper, replace the lid closely and quickly,
            and stew for three-quarters of an hour. It must be
            cooked slowly, else it will burn. The whole is cooked
            by steam, and is a most delicious as well as profitable
            dish.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Mutton Stuffed and Rolled.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>4 lbs. Mutton.</item>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                        <item>Bread-crumbs.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Parsley.</item>
                        <item>Herbs.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Procure a nice breast of mutton; take off the
            shoulder-blade; take all the bones out; cut off any
            superfluous edges of fat, and, with a rolling-pin,
            flatten the mutton by beating it well. Now take a
            breakfast-cupful of bread-crumbs, a table-spoonful of
            finely-chopped parsley, a teaspoonful of chopped herbs
            (thym and marjoram if to be had), pepper and salt
            enough to season the whole, and, after mixing all well,
            moisten it with a little milk. Spreak the mixture
            on the mutton, and roll it tightly up, tying it with
            tape in at least three places. Place it then in a dish,
            and put it in the oven for a quarter of an hour to
            draw out a good deal of fat from it. Put two table-
            spoonfuls of this fat into a stew-pan and let it get hot;
            slice the onions and fry them till pretty brown in the
            fat; then add the mutton. Put into a basin a table-
            spoonful of flour, a little pepper and salt; rub the
            flour smooth with a very little water, and then add
            two breakfast-cupfuls of water, and mix. Now pour
            this thickening into the pan with the mutton, put on
            the lid, and let all stew very slowly for 2 hours.
            Then take up the mutton and put it on a dish, after
            cutting off the tape. Remove as much fat as possible
            from the top of the sauce, and pour it over the mutton.
            See that the sauce is not too thick.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Breast of Veal Stuffed and Rolled.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Breast of Veal.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Bacon Ham.</item>
                        <item>Breakfast-cupful Grated Bread.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take a fore-quarter of half-fed veal, or the thin part
            of the breast of fed veal, weighing about 5 or 6 lbs.
            Remove all the bones, taking care not to break the
            outside skin. Take off all the rough or uneven pieces
            of the veal in the inside, and mince them up as finely
            as possible; mince also the ham finely—it should not
            be too fat. Put the chopped meat, ham, grated bread,
            half a teaspoonful each of pepper and salt in a basin,
            and, with the hand, mix them thoroughly together;
            beat up an egg well, add it, and mix well. Lay the
            veal out on a table with the skin next to the table; spread
            the stuffing neatly over the surface of the meat, leaving
            an inch bare all round; then roll it up tightly, and
            either sew it up or tie it in several places with broad
            tape.</p>
            <p>Put a teaspoonful of butter into a stew-pan large
            enough to hold it, and when hot put in the roll of veal
            and fry it all round; add an onion chopped up; then
            put in a breakfast-cupful of water and stew gently for
            2 hours. Take it up and untie the fastenings. The
            gravy should be thickened with a dessert-spoonful of
            flour, seasoned with a table-spoonful of ketchup and a
            little salt and pepper, and strained over the veal.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>To Bake the Roll.</head>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
               <p>The veal may be put into a roasting pan with a
            breakfast-cupful of boiling water, covered with another
            pan or dish, and put into the oven for an hour-and-a-
            half. It is very nice done thus. The gravy must be
            thickened and poured over.</p>
            <p>It is good either hot or cold.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Haricot Mutton.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Shoulder of Mutton.</item>
                        <item>1 Carrot.</item>
                        <item>6 small Onions.</item>
                        <item>1 larger one.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 small Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Dripping.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Cut the mutton into neat pieces the thickness of
            chops, and about 2 inches square, as near may be.
            Put into a stew-pan a table-spoonful of good dripping,
            and let it get quite hot—which is when it begins to
            smoke. Slice the largest onion and fry it in the hot
            dripping till very brown; then lay in the mutton and
            fry all the pieces well, lifting them out as they are
            done. When all are fried, pour the dripping out of the
            pan, leaving the onions in the bottom. Now mix in a
            small basin a table-spoonful of flour, a teaspoonful of
            salt, and a little pepper, with <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> breakfast-cupfuls of
            water; stir all well and pour it into the pan, and keep
            stirring over the fire till it boils up. Strain it into a
            bowl to keep back the fried onions, and make it smooth.
            Return it to the pan and lay the chops into it; put on
            the lid and stew gently for half-an-hour.</p>
            <p>Peel the 6 small onions, and cut up the carrot and
            turnip into very neatly-shaped pieces, and put them
            in the pan; allow the whole to stew 20 minutes
            longer without stirring it, as the vegetables must not
            be broken.</p>
            <p>Dish the meat neatly with the vegetables round, and
            pour the sauce over all.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Boiled Meat Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Lean Beef.</item>
                        <item>1 Mutton Kidney.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Flour.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Baking Powder.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Put the flour into a basin; add to it a pinch of salt
            and the baking powder; then chop the suet very finely
            and mix it in, rubbing it into the flour with the fingers.
            Add as much cold water as will wet it, and make it up
            into a stiff piece of paste; then flour the table, and roll
            it out into a round piece scarcely half an inch thick.
            Take a pudding bowl that holds a pint, rub it inside
            with clean dripping, line it neatly with the paste, which
            then cut even round the edges.</p>
            <p>Mix together on a plate a table-spoonful of flour, a
            teaspoonful of salt, and half a teaspoonful of pepper for
            seasoning. Cut the meat in thin slices, dip them in the
            seasoning, and place them lightly in the basin; split
            the kidney, skin, and cut it in thin slices; dip them also
            in the seasoning, and put them into the bowl, and pour
            in a teacupful of water for gravy. Wet the edges of
            the paste on the bowl; roll out the scraps that remain
            large enough to cover the dish; place it on, press down
            at the edges, and sprinkle a little flour over the top.
            Now dip a pudding-cloth in boiling water, tie it tightly
            over the top, and plunge the pudding in plenty of
            boiling water; then boil it for <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> hours. Remove
            the cloth, and turn the pudding out on a dish.</p>
            <p>Liver and bacon mixed, or mutton, make a good
            pudding of this kind.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Steak Stewed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Steak.</item>
                        <item>1 Carrot.</item>
                        <item>1 small Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>Butter.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Have the steak tender, and cut it about three-quarters
            of an inch thick; put into a small-sized stew-pan an
            ounce of butter or dripping—the butter, however, is
            preferable—and let it become quite hot; cut the onion
            in rings, and fry it in the butter till it becomes very
            brown; also scrape and cut up the carrot and fry it as
            well. This frying of the vegetables brown colours the
            gravy nicely. When quite brown, lift the vegetables
            out on a plate, and put the steak in to fry on both
            sides; it should be fried crisp, so as to shut up the
            pores of the meat and keep the juice in. If any butter
            remains in the pan, it should be poured out. The
            vegetables are then returned to the pan, and the meat
            placed on the top of them; cut up the turnip in
            smallish pieces, and add it; a leaf of celery is a great
            improvement. Now put into a basin a small table-
            spoonful of flour with salt and pepper to taste, and
            rub it smooth with a little cold water; when quite
            smooth, add a breakfast-cupful and a half of cold
            water, and stir; now pour this into the stew pan, and
            put it on the fire to come to boiling point; after that
            it must be allowed to simmer very slowly for an
            hour-and-a-half. Serve the steak on a hot dish, and
            strain the sauce over it, as by this time all the
            substance has been extracted from the vegetables.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Beef Steak Pie.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> lbs. of Steak.</item>
                        <item>2 Mutton Kidneys.</item>
                        <item>Seasoning.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Butter.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Cut the steak very thinly, and dip it in a seasoning
            made of a table-spoonful of flour, a teaspoonful of salt,
            and half a teaspoonful of pepper. Roll up the seasones
            pieces of steak, and lay them in a pie-dish; put a layer
            of meat in the bottom of the dish; skin the mutton
            kidneys, or half an ox kidney, and cut them up in
            thin slices, leaving out the fat in the middle of the
            kidney; dip them also in the seasoning; repeat till
            the meat is used up and the dish is full; pile it high
            in the middle, put in some water in the dish for gravy,
            and then make the crust as follows:—</p>
            <p>Beat up an egg on a plate; put on a board half
            a pound of flour, quarter pound of butter, half a tea-
            spoonful baking-powder; mix the baking-powder with
            the flour; chop the butter into pieces the size of a nut
            among the flour; now pour about a gill of water in the
            middle of the flour, and the half of the egg; with these
            make it up into a stiff paste, which roll out length-
            ways, keeping the edges as straight as possible and
            about a quarter of an inch thick; fold this piece in
            three, turn it round, and roll lengthways again; fold in
            three, turn it round, and roll once more. This time it
            may be rolled rather larger than the size required for
            the dish. Wet the edge of the dish, and put a narrow
            band of paste round; wet the band, place on it the
            remainder of the paste, which cut to the size of the
            dish, then notch the edges very neatly, and brush over
            with the half egg you have left. Make a large hole in
            the top, and into this put the ends of some leaf-shaped
            pieces of paste, with an ornament in the centre; egg
            the leaves, and bake. After the crust begins to brown,
            cover it with a buttered paper, and bake for <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Steak and Onions Fried.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Steak.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>3 Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Ketchup.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take 3 onions, slice them in rings, and put them
            in a small basin of cold water to soak for an hour to
            take away some of the strong flavour. Now take a
            large frying-pan, and put in it an ounce of suet
            chopped up, or dripping, and, after allowing it to get
            hot, put in the steak (which should be full half an
            inch thick) to fry. It should be on a very moderate
            fire, and turned very often till it is cooked, which it
            will be in about 8 minutes. If it is firm to the
            touch when pressed, it is ready. The onions should
            be drained and put between the folds of a towel to dry,
            then put in the pan with the steak if there is roo,
            and fried at the same time; they should have a little
            colour, without being over-browned. The steak is
            dished up with the onions round it. Put in the pan a
            teaspoonful of flour, sprinkled in, a table-spoonful
            of ketchup, pepper and salt, and a teacupful of water;
            stir them till they boil, and strain the sauce over the
            steak. The flour and the ketchup may be omitted.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Hough of Beef Stewed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hough of Beef</item>
                        <item>Carrot.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Have a nice piece of the thick part of the hough,
            about 4 or 5 lbs.; take all the marrow from the bone,
            cut it in little bits, and put in a stew-pan on the
            fire. After the marrow has become quite hot, put in
            the piece of meat and fry it brown all round, par-
            ticularly at the ends, to shut up the pores of the meat;
            when quite well fried, pour off any remains of fat in
            the pot, and add a pint of water; put the lid closely on,
            and allow it to stew <hi rend="italic">very</hi> slowly for an hour; now add
            a carrot cut in quarters, a turnip neatly cut, and 2
            onions halved. Allow all to stew for an hour-and-a-
            half longer. Slow stewing makes the muscles of the
            shin to swell and become very tender; but if cooked
            too fast, this piece of meat is spoiled. This is a profit-
            able as well as a very nice dish, if stewed <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> or 3
            hours. Put the meat on a dish with the vegetables
            round, and the gravy poured over.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—Care must be taken that the gravy does not dry
            up too much, and that the stewing is extremely slow.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Scotch Collop.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Steak.</item>
                        <item>1 oz. Butter or Dripping.</item>
                        <item>3 Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 oz. Flour.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take a pound of shoulder-steak, cut very thinly;
            put in a stew-pan an ounce of butter or dripping, and
            let it get quite hot; then put in the steak cut in pieces
            about 3 inches square or so; let this fry well on
            both sides till the outside is crisp; sprinkle in a table-
            spoonful of flour; stir it round till it has mixed well;
            then add the onions, either cut in rings or chopped up,
            some pepper and salt, three-quarters of a pint of water,
            and stir until it boils up; after that let it simmer very
            slowly for an hour-and-a-half. This stew should be
            kept quite below boiling point until it is done, as
            boiling hardens the meat.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Irish Stew.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Mutton.</item>
                        <item>3 Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> lbs. Potatoes.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Cut up the meat in rather small pieces, and put it
            in a stew-pan with a cupful of water, and allow it to
            stew for half-an-hour. Pare the potatoes and slice
            them about half an inch thick, and put them in a
            basin; pour over them plenty of boiling water, and
            cover them up. The same may be done to the onions
            if a strong taste is objected to, but for this dish the
            onions should only be chopped and added. Drain the
            potatoes when the meat has stewed for a quarter of an
            hour, and put them in the stew-pan on the top of the
            meat; add the onions, pepper and salt, a cupful of
            more water, and stew very slowly for three-quarters of
            an hour. By this time the potatoes will be cooked,
            but not pulpy. Dish high in a plate and serve hot.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Toad in a Hole.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Flour.</item>
                        <item>1 pinch Salt.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Sausages.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3/4</num> pint Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Put into a basin the flour and salt; beat the egg
            well, and, after mixing it with the milk, pour gradually
            among the flour, beating it with a spoon. When quite
            smooth, pour it into a pudding dish; put the sausages
            in among the batter, and bake for three-quarters of an
            hour.</p>
            <p>Pieces of apples, some gooseberries, rhubarb, or pieces
            of cold meat or fish, may be substituted for the
            sausages, and all make a good dish. The fruit requires
            a little sugar, and sugar must also be used along with
            the pudding.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Scotch Haggis.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Sheep's Pluck.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Oatmeal.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Sheep's Stomach.</item>
                           <item>1 Onion.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Procure a sheep's pluck and stomach-bag; wash the
            pluck well, and put it on in a pot to boil, allowing the
            windpipe to hang out of the pot, so that any impurities
            will come out by it; boil gently from <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> to 2 hours.</p>
            <p>Get the stomach-bag nicely cleaned by the butcher;
            wash it thoroughly, and put it on in cold water, and
            bring it to the boil, which will cause the bag to contract.
            Take it out of the pot immediately, wash and scrape
            it well, and lay it in salt and water until needed.
            Mince the best part of the lungs and the heart, leaving
            out all grisly parts; grate the best parts of the liver,
            and put all in a large basin. Toast well the oatmeal,
            and add to it the contents of the basin. Chop the suet
            very finely; add a middling-sized onion very finely
            chopped up, 2 teaspoonfuls of salt and a teaspoonful
            of pepper, and a breakfast-cupful of the liquor in which
            the pluck was boiled to moisten, and mix the whole.</p>
            <p>Now take up the stomach-bag; keep the fat or
            smooth side inside, and fill it up, but not quite full;
            sew up the opening, and put in boiling water to boil
            gently for 3 hours.</p>
            <p>Prick the haggis several times with a darning-needle
            to prevent it from bursting; also put a plate under it
            to prevent it sticking to the bottom of the pot.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Kidney Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>3 Mutton Kidneys.</item>
                        <item>2 teacupfuls of Bread-
                        crumbs.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful of Suet.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Nutmeg.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item>Parsley.</item>
                        <item>Herbs.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Skin the kidneys and mince them very finely; also
            mince the suet, and put both in a basin with the
            bread-crumbs; add a teaspoonful of chopped parsley,
            a very little chopped thyme and grated nutmeg, half a 
            teaspoonful of salt and a quarter teaspoonful of pepper,
            and mix all well together. Beat up the egg and mix
            it with the milk; then stir both into the pudding.
            Pour it into a plain shape or bowl buttered; cover
            with paper, and steam for an hour. Pour brown sauce
            over it, and serve hot.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Roast Bullock's Heart.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Bullock's Heart.</item>
                        <item>6 table-spoonfuls Bread Crumbs.</item>
                        <item>2 table-spoonfuls Chopped Suet.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful Chopped Parsley.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> table-spoonful Herbs.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>Salt and Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash out all the cavities of the heart thoroughly
            both with hot and cold water, and dry the inside.
            Mix all the above ingredients together, seasoning
            nicely, adding and mixing the eggs last. Stuff with
            this all the cavities. Cut some of the flaps at the top
            off, and sew together the opening. Put the heart into
            a sauce-pan of hot water, and boil 1 hour. Afterward
            cover with a thickly-greased paper, and put in the
            oven to roast for <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours. Serve with brown sauce.</p>
            <p>The cavities may all be cut into one and a large
            opening made.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Fowl Trussed and Boiled.</head>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wipe off all the brown partiles left when singeing;
            empty the fowl neatly and carefully, removing only
            the stomach and windpipe at throat end. Wipe the
            fowl out with hot and cold water—it is best to do this
            with a cloth dipped in hot water; dry it thoroughly.
            If the bird is at all "high" it may be rinsed with a
            little vinegar, afterwards washed with water.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>To Truss it.</head>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
               <p>Fold back the first point of the wings; take off the
                  legs, and push the thigh bone well up. Take a skewer,
                  and with it catch up the end of the wing and the back
                  joint of the leg; run it over the back, and catch the
                  other leg and wing in the same way; put a trussing-
                  needle and a bit of string through the side bone of the
                  fowl over the ends of the legs, and tie it firmly round
                  the end of the back-bone.</p>
               <p>Have a pot with 2 quarts of water boiling, into
                  which put the fowl with the breast down, and boil it
                  1 or <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours, according to age. When boiled, take it
                  up, remove the skewer and string, and pour over it
                  egg sauce, or any other white sauce preferable.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>A Good Breakfast Dish.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>4 lbs. Pork.</item>
                        <item>1 Pork Tongue.</item>
                        <item>Sage.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Onions.</item>
                        <item>Pepper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take a piece of pickled pork, the thin part of the
            belly, which should be about 8 or 9 inches broad,
            and rather more than that long; take out the bones
            and flatten it a little; get a good pork tongue, which,
            like the pork, has been salted for a few days; sprinkle
            on the pork a few leaves of sage chopped finely, and a
            middling-sized onion chopped; also some pepper. Roll
            the tongue up in the middle of the pork into a nice
            roll; bind it outside with a long slip of calico, rolled
            round neatly and tightly. Put it on covered with cold
            water, and boil gently for 4 or 5 hours, allowing it to
            become nearly cold in the water, and when quite cold
            remove the bandage.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head></head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Sheep's Liver.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. fat Pork Ham.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Ketchup.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the liver well, making a few cuts through it
            in order to allow the blood to be washed out. Dry it
            well, and cut it into slices about half an inch thick.
            Mix on a plate some flour with a little salt and pepper,
            and dip each slice in this mixture.</p>
            <p>Cut the ham in neat, small pieces, and put it on a
            hot, clean frying-pan to fry lightly. Take up the
            pieces of ham on a plate to keep hot; put the liver
            on the pan to fry—about 8 minutes—turning the
            slices once. The fat left on the pan, after the ham is
            fried, should be sufficient to fry the liver. Dish it
            neatly with a small bit of ham on each piece of liver.</p>
            <p>Put into the frying-pan a small table-spoonful of
            flour, a little pepper and salt, and stir till it gets mixed
            with the remains of the fat; pour in a breakfast-cupful
            of water and a table-spoonful of ketchup, if to be had,
            and stir over the fire till it boild. Pour or strain the
            sauce over the dish of liver and bacon. Onions are
            frequently fried in the dripping instead of the ham.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Sausage Rolls.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Dripping.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful Baking
                        Powder.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3/4</num> lb. Cold Meat.</item>
                        <item>Ketchup.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Chop up any kind of cooked meat very finely.</p>
            <p>On the table where it was chopped, mix with it a
            table-spoonful of flour, a teaspoonful of salt, and a little
            pepper. Put nearly a teacupful of water into a pan,
            and a table-spoonful of ketchup, or a little gravy if to
            be had; add the mixture of meat and flour, and stir
            over the fire till it comes to boiling heat, when the
            flour is cooked; afterwards turn it out on a plate to
            get cool. This mixture should be made very tasty and
            nice, and quite a thick paste.</p>
            <p>Put in a basin a pound of flour, a pinch of salt, and
            the baking powder; add the dripping broken into
            pieces the size of a small nut; make it into a stiff paste
            with water; roll it out lengthways and quite thin;
            then fold it in three, turn it roung, and roll it again
            lengthways; fold it in three and turn it round, and
            roll once more. This time roll it in any way most
            convenient, and about one-eighth of an inch thick.
            Cut the sheet of paste into pieces 5 inches square;
            wet the edges of each square and place on each a
            spoonful of the meat; turn one side of the paste over
            on the meat, and overlap it with the other side; press
            the ends down with the back of a knife, and place the
            sausage rolls on a greased oven plate. Brush them
            over with a beaten egg, and bake about a quarter of an
            hour in a quick oven.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Curried Rabbit.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Rabbit.</item>
                        <item>2 Onions.</item>
                        <item>1 oz. Butter.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Apple.</item>
                        <item>Curry Powder.</item>
                        <item>Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take a nice rabbit, empty and wash it very well,
            and, after drying it thoroughly, cut it up into small
            joints. Have a small stew-pan, and put the butter in
            it to get quite hot; peel and chop up the onions, and fry
            them a very pale brown; add the pieces of rabbit, and
            fry them on all sides; peel and chop up the apple,
            which also add; stir in a teaspoonful of curry powder,
            a pinch of salt, and mix them well with the meat;
            add a teacupful of water, and stew for an hour. Dish
            with a border of boiled rice round it.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Rice, to Boil.</head>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To boil rice dry and light for curry, or even to use
            with jam, requires a little care. Wash half a pound
            of rice well, and put it into boiling water with a little
            salt. Let it boil for 8 minutes, then drain it; pour
            some cold water over it, and drain it again. Return
            it to the sauce-pan; put the lid closely on, and let it
            steam on a slow fire for a quarter of an hour. It will
            then be found dry and light. Patna rice is best, and
            is also cheapest.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Tripe and Onions.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>3 lbs. Tripe.</item>
                        <item>1 pint Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>3 Onions.</item>
                        <item>Flour, Pepper, and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Get the tripe cleaned by the butcher, if possible,
            but wash it well. Put it on a sauce-pan covered
            with cold water, and bring it to the boil. When
            it just boils, take out the pieces of tripe and put them
            in a basin of cold water to wash again; take each
            piece out on a table and scrape it well on both sides,
            and cut it up in pieces about 3 inches square.
            When well scraped, washed, and cut up, put it on again,
            covered with cold water, and bring to the boil, and
            allow it to boil gently for 5 hours. It is absolutely
            necessary to keep it boiling for this length of time to
            make the tripe tender enough. Now pour off the
            water (which can be used to make soup), and replace it
            with the milk, which bring to the boil. Have the
            onions parboiled; chop them up, and add them to the
            tripe and milk.</p>
            <p>Put into a small basin a dessert-spoonful of flour,
            a little pepper and salt, and rub them smooth
            with a little cold milk; add the flour, etc., to
            the sauce-pan containing the tripe, and allow all
            to boil for a quarter of an hour. Dish up, and serve
            very hot.</p>
            <p>Tripe is very nutritious and also very digestible,
            taking a much shorter time to digest than any other
            animal food, and is consequently an excellent food for
            the convalescent.</p>
            <p>The liquor in which tripe has been boiled makes
            excellent potato or pea soup.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Tripe Stewed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>3 lbs. Tripe.</item>
                        <item>3 Onions.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>If the tripe is preferred brown, put into a stew-
            pan an ounce of dripping, and make it quite hot;
            slice the onions, and fry them in the dripping a
            brown colour; sprinkle in a table-spoonful of flour,
            and stir till quite mixed and a little brown; now
            add three-quarters of a pint of water, with pepper
            and salt, and the pieces of tripe (prepared and cut
            up exactly as in the preceding recipe), and stew
            gently for half-an-hour.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Tripe, to Clean.</head>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>If the tripe cannot be got cleaned, empty and wash
            it thoroughly with cold water; then put it in a pot
            with cold water, in which there is a good piece of soda;
            let it get hot, but on no account must it be allowed to
            boil; then take it out and scrape it white. Let it lie
            all night in cold water with a little butter milk in it,
            and next day it will be ready to be cooked.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Sea Pie.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Meat.</item>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                        <item>1 Carrot.</item>
                        <item>1 Turnip.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Baking Powder.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Put the meat, cut in rather small pieces, into
            middling-sized stew-pan; cut up the carrot and turnip
            in small pieces, and sprinkle them over the meat, and
            also the onion, chopped finely; then pepper and salt
            to taste. Pour in water to cover the meat and vege-
            tables; set the stew-pan on the fire, and bring to the
            boil.</p>
            <p>Put into a basin the flour and suet chopped very
            finely, and rub them together; add a pinch of salt and
            half a teaspoonful of baking powder, and mix all well.
            Make this into a paste with cold water; roll it out
            into a round cake the size of the stew-pan, and put it
            neatly upon the top of the meat and vegetables; cover
            closely with the lid, and let it stew gently for an hour-
            and-a-half. Lift the paster carefully off, dish the meat
            and vegetables, and place the cake of paste on the top,
            and serve.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Cold Meat Rolls.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Cooked Meat.</item>
                        <item>8 Cooked Potatoes.</item>
                        <item>1 Onion.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Butter.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Chop up the cooked meat and the onion (also
            cooked) very finely, and season with pepper and salt.</p>
            <p>Mash the potatoes smoothly, and add to them a tea-
            spoonful of butter or dripping melted, then whisk
            them over the fire to dry.</p>
            <p>Turn the whole out on the table, and add as much
            flour as the potatoes will take up, and roll the potato
            paste out about a quarter of an inch thick. Cut it
            into pieces about 6 inches square. Place on each piece
            a spoonful of the chopped meat; wet the edges, and
            double the paster over one side above the other, and
            press the ends down. Place these oblong rolls on a
            greased tin, and bake till they become a light brown
            colour, or fry them in hot fat in a frying-pan.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Mutton Cutlets.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. of Mutton from the ribs.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item>Some find Bread-crumbs.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        <item>Some Mashed Potatoes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The mutton for this dish should be cut from the
            back ribs above the loin, and is best not to be too
            heavy mutton. The same part of lamb may be used
            instead of mutton. The cutlets should have a bone
            in each, and the bone should be 5 or 6 inches long.
            Saw or chop off the chine bone, that, is the bone at the
            thick end, as it spoils the shape of the cutlet. Then
            flatten each with a wetter chopper; afterwards trim
            them neatly, leaving half an inch of bone bare at the
            top. Sprinkle a little pepper and salt over each: now
            beat up the egg on a plate, and dip the cutlets in this
            and then into the bread-crumbs. Pat each cutlet
            either with the hand or a knife, to put the bread-
            crumbs smooth and firmly into it.</p>
            <p>Now put a table-spoonful of sweet dripping into a
            frying-pan; when it is quite hot, put in the cutlets and
            fry a golden colour on each side.</p>
            <p>Have the potatoes nicely boiled and mashed; make
            them into a heap in the centre of a dish, and put the
            cutlets neatly round; some good brown or tomato
            sauce may be served with the dish.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Cold Meat Mince.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Cooked Meat.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>Bread.</item>
                        <item>Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Onion, Carrot and Turnip.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Ketchup.</item>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take a pound of lean cooked meat and chop it up
            very finely; soak a thick slice of bread in milk, and
            press the milk well out when quite soaked; beat it up
            with a fork, add it to the beef, and mix all well
            together; add pepper and salt to taste; now beat up
            one egg, and mix it with the meat and bread. Have a
            nice deep pudding-dish, butter it well inside, and cut
            up, in small pieces, a hard-boiled egg. Ornament the
            bottom and sides of the pudding-dish very neatyl with
            the egg; press the mixture in, and when baked for an
            hour, turn it out gently. Make a sauce as in recipe
            for Brown Sauce (page 91); use the bones to make
            the stock for it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="58" type="chapter" xml:id="veg">
            <head>VEGETABLES.</head>
            <p>VEGETABLES are most valuable food, and can easily
            sustain life and promote health without the aid of
            animal food, or (more properly speaking) butcher meat.
            Vegetable food, however, generally requires the addition
            of milk, butter, or cheese, which are animal foods.
            Many vegetables, such as grain, beans, peas, lentils, etc.,
            are highly nitrogenous or flesh-forming; they all contain
            a large proportion of mineral substances, and many are
            carbonaceous, or body-warming foods in a high degree;
            so that in vegetable diet the wants of the body, under
            ordinary circumstances, are all supplied. All green
            vegetables are anti-scorbutic, or blood-purifiers; they
            help to dissolve other food in the stomach and assist
            digestion, and, as they contain a great deal of water,
            are particularly suitable to be used in hot weather.
            The blood contains a great many mineral substances as
            well as salts; and vegetables and water supply some of
            those necessaries. Wheat contains more of the mineral
            matter of which the bones are formed than any other
            food; and all growing children should have a dietary
            consisting of bread or food largely composed of flour.</p>
            <p>When green vegetables, such as cabbage, leeks, etc.,
            are not easily digested, or seem to disagree with the
            stomach, let them be boiled half the necessary time,
            the water in which they are being boiled should then
            be thrown away and replaced with fresh boiling water,
            and the requisite time completed; by doing this,
            vegetables will be found to agree with very delicate
            stomachs. The same process may be advantageously
            followed with potatoes that are old and out of season,
            and will remove the bitter taste and rather injurious
            juice which their age engenders.</p>
            <p>Vegetables require sufficient and very careful
            cooking, their flavour and appearance being easily
            spoiled by want of attention. Every country abounds
            with the vegetables most suited to its climate, and
            they are so obviously intended for the use of the
            inhabitants that it is impossible to avoid the inference
            that they ought to form a very large proportion of our
            diet. In hot countries extremely watery vegetables and
            fruits abound, such as melons, pumpkins, etc., for the
            comfort and pleasure of the inhabitants; and in our
            own country, the vegetables that are most abundant
            are precisely those that are most valuable for our food.
            Fruits also ought to enter largely into our diet. If
            ripe, they cannot be too freely partaken of by all, the
            young especially; and when not quite ripe, subjected
            to some process of cooking.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Green Vegetables, to Boil.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Cabbage.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Soak the cabbage (after it has been well washed and
            the withered leaves removed from the outside) in salt
            and water for an hour. This makes all insects come
            out and freshens the cabbage. If the cabbage is large
            and firm, cut the stalk about 3 inches deep,
            or rather more, and then cut again in the opposite
            direction; this opens up the heart of the cabbage and
            allows the water to penetrate; have a sauce-pan with
            plenty of boiling water, having in it a table-spoonful
            of salt, and a little carbonate of soda the size of a
            pea, or a very little sugar; put the cabbage in head
            downwards, holding it down till it sinks to the bottom;
            when the water boils again, take the lid off and let it
            boil the rest of the time with the lid off (this preserves
            the colour), from 20 minutes to half-an-hour. When
            so tender in the stalk that you can easily put a fork
            in, it is ready; lit it out on a drainer and press the
            water well out of it. It may be served with French
            sauce or plain melted butter.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—A piece of bread, tied in a linen rag and put
            in the water, prevents the unpleasant smell the boiling
            of green vegetables causes in a house.</p>
            <div n="60" type="section">
               <head>To Boil Green Peas.</head>
               <p>Shell and wahs the peas, and put them in boiling
               water with a little sugar, salt, and a sprig of mint in
               it; let them boil for about 20 minutes, or perhaps
               a little longer if the peas are old. Drain them in a
               cullender, take out the mint, and shake a small bit of
               butter and a little pepper and salt among them, and
               serve.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
               <head>Cauliflower, to Boil.</head>
               <p>Wash carefully, and allow the cauliflower to lie in
               salted water for an hour at least; then trim the leaves
               even with the top of the flower, removing the coarser
               outside leaves altogether.</p>
               <p>Put it head downwards in plenty of boiling water,
               salted (just enough salt to taste the water), and a small
               pinch of carbonate of soda, or half a teaspoonful of
               sugar. Let it boil rapidly for about a quarter of an
               hour, with the lid off the pot to allow the gas to escape
               from the cooking vegetable. When a fork can be put
               into one of the outside leaves easily, it is ready. Take
               it up in a cullender to drain, and send it to table with
               white sauce or melted butter over it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
               <head>To Stew Carrots.</head>
               <p>Scrape the carrots and cut them in nicely-shaped
               pieces, about an inch long, or in the form of young
               carrots; put them in a saucepan with as much stock
               as will cover them, and a teaspoonful of sugar; let
               them stew gently till tender—about an hour; pile
               them high in a dish, add a little chopped parsley to
               the stock, which should be much reduced, and pour it
               over them, and serve.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
               <head>Turnips, to Boil and Mash.</head>
               <p>Peel the turnips thickly, taking off all the fibrous
               skin, and cut them in quarters, or in smaller pieces.
               Put them in boiling water, with salt, and boil quickly
               about three-quarters of an hour; drain them dry and
               mash them well, either with a fork, or rub them
               through an iron sieve. Return them to a clean
               sauce-pan with half an ounce of butter, pepper, and
               salt, and stir till hot and dry; add a little cream, and
               dish in a pyramid, on a plate.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Brussels Sprouts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 lb. Brussels Sprouts.</item>
                        <item>1 oz. Butter.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>Put the sprouts in plenty of cold water to wash
               them well. Take each sprout and trim the stalk,
               cutting off any withered leaves on the outside, and put
               them in a basin of clean cold water. Have plenty
               of boiling water (salted), and small pinch of car-
               bonater of soda in it; drain the sprouts, and put
               them in the pot to boil, with the lid off, for about 10
               minutes; drain them in a cullender, and return them
               to the pot with half an ounce of butter and a little
               pepper and salt. Shake them about in the pot gently
               to send the butter quite over them; dish them neatly
               ina pile on a dish, and serve.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Haricot Beans Boiled.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Beans.</item>
                           <item>1 dessert-spoonful of Dripping.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Butter.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 table-spoonful of Chopped
                           Parsley.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Soak the beans in cold water for 24 hours. Put
               them on to boil in 3 breakfast-cupfuls of cold water,
               with a dessert-spoonful of dripping in it, or a small
               piece of any fresh fat. Let them boil about an hour,
               till the beans are soft, but not broken. Drain them,
               and add the butter and parsley, pepper and salt, and
               shake them about in the pan till the butter and parsley
               are well mixed over them; then serve.</p>
               <p>No salt must be used when boiling the beans, as it
               would make them hard and tough. Melted butter or
               tomato sauce may be poured over the beans, in which
               case they make an excellent substitute for meat.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Spanish Onions Boiled.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Onion.</item>
                           <item>1 teacupful of Milk.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 dessert-spoonful of Flour.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Take the outside skin neatly from the onion, and
               put in plenty of boiling water (salted) and with half
               a teaspoonful of sugar, and allow it to boil. An onion
               weighing 1 lb. requires to boil an hour-and-a-half;
               weighing <num type="fraction">3/4</num> of a lb., 1 hour; <num type="fraction">1/2</num> a lb., three-quarters of
               an hour. Drain the onion from the water, and mix
               the flour and milk, salt and pepper, together. Put the
               mixture in a small pan to boil, stirring it constantly,
               then pour it over the onion, and serve.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
               <head>Potatoes Boiled.</head>
               <p>Potatoes are a most valuable article of food, and
               undoubtedly deserve and require great care in their
               preparation. The skin is designed and fitted to preserve
               the valuable juices which the potato contains, and that
               potato is not well cooked which allows those juices to
               excape. All succulent vegetables possess anti-scorbutic
               or blood-purifying powers—the potato possesses such
               properties in a high degree. A potato cooked, keeping
               the skin entire, will digest much more quickly than if
               the skin is broken and the juices allowed to flow into
               the water in the pot; and a potato roasted in its skin
               is by far the lightest and most digestible way in which
               to prepare it for an invalid.</p>
               <p>Potatoes are really best to be boiled in their skins,
               although there are two exceptions to this rule—one is
               when the potatoes are unripe, when they just come in;
               and the second is when they are old and out of season,
               in the spring and early summer. In the first of those
               cases the potato is very watery, being unripe, and
               is best to have the skin scraped off and put in boiling
               water and boiled rapidly, as this draws out some of
               the water and makes the potato better food. In the
               second case, the potato acquires a bitter taste when it
               gets old, and is better pared and even soaked for a
               short time in cold water, before boiling in the usual
               way. Potatoes, however, should <hi rend="italic">never</hi> be soaked longer
               than 1 or 2 hours, as one of the principal components
               of the potato is starch, and with soaking in water the
               starch gradually loosens, comes out into the water, and
               is lost, as may be seen in the white sediment that
               remains in the bottom of a basin in which the potatoes
               have been soaked.</p>
               <p>A few simple rules may be given now for the boiling
               of the potatoes:—</p>
               <list rend="numbered">
                  <item>Select the potatoes all one size, or as nearly as
                  possible. It is impossible to boil small and large
                  potatoes properly together.</item>
                  <item>Barely cover the potatoes with water.</item>
                  <item>Add as much salt as tastes the water.</item>
                  <item>Bring them slowly to the boil.</item>
                  <item>Boil the potatoes slowly; the larger the potatoes
                  are the slower they should be boiled, because the heat
                  takes longer to penetrate to the heart. For very large
                  potatoes a little cold water may be added once or twice,
                  to prolong the boiling.</item>
                  <item>Drain them before the skin cracks in the least,
                  but not <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> dry.</item>
                  <item>Allow them to steam 5 or 10 minutes with the
                  lid on, and a few minutes with it off. They may now
                  be quickly peeled and dished up.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
               <head>Potatoes Mashed.</head>
               <p>The best way to mash potatoes, in a plain way, is to
               take a strong fork and whisk them with it till
               they become smooth and light. The longer they are
               whisked the lighter they become. Add a very little
               sweet milk, and stir them well; then dish them up
               very neatly in a heap.</p>
               <p>When potatoes are pared before boiling, it should be
               very thinly indeed, as the best part is next the skin;
               then put into cold water at once, and boil according to
               the directions given.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Leeks, to Boil.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>6 Leeks.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Butter.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3/4</num> pint Milk.</item>
                        <item>1 slice Toast.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Select leeks about the thickness of a finger, and cut
            them all about the same length, leaving scarcely any
            of the green part on, and wash them very carefully
            and trim them neatly. Tie them in a bundle, and put
            into a small stew-pan, with boiling water and a little
            salt, to parboil for 5 minutes, when they should be
            drained and afterwards put into a clean sauce-pan, with
            enough milk to cover, and the sugar. Let them stew
            in this till tender, about 20 minutes or more,
            according to age, and dish them on toast. Thicken
            the milk with half an ounce of butter and half an
            ounce of flour kneaded together, which season to taste,
            and, after allowing it to boil, pour over the leeks.
            They may be cut in inch-lengths if preferred, and
            piled high on the toast.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Parsnips, to Boil.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>4 Parsnips.</item>
                           <item>1 teaspoonful Flour.</item>
                           <item>1 teaspoonful Butter.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teacupful of Milk.</item>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the parsnips clean, scraping away the
            discoloured parts. Have a sauce-pan with plenty of
            boiling waiter, and enough salt to taste the water well,
            into which put the parsnips, and boil them for about
            three-quarters of an hour, or till tender; then drain
            them, scrape the skin entirely off, and cut them into
            slices. Mix the flour and butter together, and put
            both in a small stew-pan, with the milk, pepper, and
            salt, and stir till boiling; add the parsnips, and shake
            over the fire till they are well heated up, and serve
            very hot.</p>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Parsnips, to Mash.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>4 Parsnips.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Butter.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item>Pepper and Salt.</item>
                           <item>Vinegar.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Wash an boil the parsnips as described above;
               when sufficiently boiled, scrape clean, and mash up
               thoroughly with a fork. Put them into a small sauce-
               pan, with the butter, pepper, salt, and a few drops of
               vinegar; stir over the fire till they are quite hot. Dish
               in a pile, and serve hot.</p>
               <p>A table-spoonful of tomato improves the parsnips,
               and may be used instead of vinegar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
               <head>Red Cabbage, to Pick.</head>
               <p>Take a nice, firm red cabbage and wash it well,
               taking off the coarse outside leaves. Shred the cabbage
               up finely into very slender slips, and put a layer of
               the cabbage on a sieve or basket; sprinkle salt rather
               plentifully over it, and repeat till the whole is finished.
               Allow it to remain thus for 2 days, turning it over
               several times that it may drain; then put it into a jar.
               Boil a pint of vinegar with a teaspoonful of pepper
               corns, a blade of mace, and 6 cloves, and pour boiling
               over the cabbage in the jar; add a few slices of
               beetroot if convenient, which will improve the colour.</p>
               <p>Cover up tightly when cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Beetroot, to Pickle.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>6 Beetroots.</item>
                           <item>2 pints Vinegar.</item>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Ginger.</item>
                        </list>
                        <cb/>
                        <list>
                           <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Peppercorns.</item>
                           <item>1 blade Mace.</item>
                           <item>1 doz. Cloves.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Wash the beetroots gently, taking care not to break
               the fibres, as they will bleed and lose their colour. Put
               them into a sauce-pan, with boiling water tasted with
               salt, to boil for an hour-and-a-half. Peel and cut them
               in slices one-eighth inch thick, and put them in a jar.</p>
               <p>Boil a pint of of vinegar with the peppercorns, mace,
               cloves, ginger, and, when boiled, add to it a pint of
               cold vinegar. Pour the whole over the beetroots in
               the jar, and when quite cold cover tightly.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="68" type="chapter" xml:id="puddings">
            <head>PUDDINGS.</head>
            <p>THE most important article that enters into the composition
            of puddings is milk. It is a perfect food, and
            contains all the substances necessary to sustain life,
            and in the young of animals does sustain life for a 
            lengthened period. It is converted into solid food in
            the stomach on the same principle by which milk is
            converted into cheese. The gastric juices in the
            stomach separate the milk, so that there is a solid part
            like curd, and a liquid like whey. Two cupfuls of
            new milk contain as much nourishment as a mutton
            chop, and the same quantity of milk makes an ounce
            of chees; so that an ounce of cheese contains as
            much nourishment or nitrogenous food as a mutton
            chop. This gives an idea of the value of milk as food.
            The cream of the milk is carbonaceous, and milk itself
            contains a large proportion of mineral food.</p>
            <p>Eggs are much used in the composition of puddings,
            and it is desirable that their value be well
            understood. They are very nutritious, and contain 
            a great deal of nitrogenous food in a remarkably
            concentrated form.</p>
            <p>A hen's egg of averag size weighs <num type="fraction">1 3/4</num> ounces, and
            contains water, albumen, fat, oil, and mineral matter.
            It is said that 18 eggs contain as much flesh-forming
            substance and other nutrients as would suffice for an
            adult man for a day, and it would be necessary to
            consume 70 lbs. of fruit, such as a pear, to provide the
            same amount of albumen or nitrogenous food. This
            very strikingly shows the concentrated nourishment
            to be found in an egg. Eggs contain as much heat-giving
            and glesh-forming substance as an equal weight
            of butcher meat.</p>
            <p>Puddings composed principally of milk and eggs
            should be very gently cooked, as a very strong heat will
            cause them to curdle. Puddings with suet should be
            well cooked, as suet takes a long time to combine with
            the other materials of which puddings are composed.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Rice</hi> makes excellent puddings, and although in itself
            not nitrogenous food, yet, combined with milk and eggs,
            is sufficiently nourishing, and very light. Rice is principally
            composed of starch, and is carbonaceous; on
            that account it is excellent for the young and old,
            who require food that is warming and easily digested.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Macaroni</hi> is a composition of wheaten flour made
            into a kind of paste. There are many varieties of this,
            which go under the name of Italian Pastes. Macaroni
            is the cheapest and most useful article which can be
            used for puddings. It is nitrogenous, because it is
            made of wheat, and on that account is much more
            strengthening than rice. The nitrogenous principle
            in wheat is called gluten. Combined with cheese,
            macaroni is particularly good, and in that form is much
            used in foreign countries, and it is well worthy of
            being more extensively used in this country than it
            has formerly been.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Semolina</hi> resembles ground rice in its grain, but is
            of a yellow colour, and is a portion of wheat which is
            not finely ground. It makes very good puddings, and
            can be used in any form in which rice is used, and is
            much more strengthening.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Corn Flour</hi> is almost wholly starch, and on that account
            is fattening and warming, but not strengthening.
            It is not sufficiently nitrogenous to be the constant
            food of infants as it does not develop the muscles and
            flesh sufficiently. Boiled or baked flour is much better
            food for infants than corn flour.</p>
            <p>Puddings are much lighter steamed than boiled.
            Steaming means that a very little water is put into a
            pot or pan, having a close lid. When the water boils,
            the pudding is put in, and it cooks in the steam.
            There should only be enough water to keep steam in
            the pot; but care must be taken that it does not all
            evaporate, and the pudding as well as the pot get
            burned. Boiling means that a pudding is covered
            with either a cloth or lid, and plunged overhead in
            boiling water, and cooked so for the necessary time.
            This generally makes a pudding heavier and less
            digestible. A lid is particularly to be avoided, as it so
            hermetically seals the pudding that none of the gas
            engendered by the cooking escapes, and it cannot be
            either so light or wholesome.</p>
            <p>Puddings with suet, much butter, or fat of any kind,
            are greatly improved by having a sauce served with
            them; as cold milk or cream is liable to congeal the
            fat and render it unpleasant. A few recipes for
            Pudding Sauces will be given in their place.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Bread Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 thick slices of Bread.</item>
                        <item>2 table-spoonfuls of Marmalade.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 breakfast-cupful of Milk.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Cut the crust from the bread, and break the soft
            part into a basin. Boil the milk and pour it over the
            bread. Cover the basin with a plate, and stand it
            aside for ten minutes. Then with a fork whisk it
            up till it forms a pulp. Beat up the eggs, and
            stir them in, mixing well; to which add a table-spoonful
            of marmalade and mix all together. Butter a
            basin or plain mould, and spread a table-spoonful of
            marmalade over the bottom of it. Pour in the pudding
            and cover it with a buttered paper; then steam for an
            hour. Turn it our on a plate and allow the marmalade
            to pour round it like sauce.</p>
            <p>Raisins may be mixed with the pudding instead of
            marmalade, and the mould ornamented with raisings
            instead of having the marmalade in the bottom.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Scrap Bread Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. scraps of Bread.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful chopped Suet
                        or Dripping.</item>
                        <item>1 handful Currants or Raisins.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful of Ground Ginger.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of Milk.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Keep all scraps of bread that are clean, and neatly
            cut from them all the brown crust. Put the bread into
            a basin of water to soak for an hour. Less time is
            required if the bread is not very hard.</p>
            <p>Have very clean hands, and after squeezing the
            water entirely out, put the bread in a dry basin, and
            add to it the sugar, the dripping or suet, and the fruit.
            Boil the milk, and pour it over the bread, etc., in the
            basin, and whisk it well up with a fork. Beat up the
            egg and add it, also the ground ginger. Butter a
            basin, into which put the pudding, and allow it to
            steam for <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours.</p>
            <p>Serve with sweet sauce.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Plum Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Bread-crumbs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Sugar.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Currants.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Valentia Raisins.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Orange Peel.</item>
                        <item>1 Lemon.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 salt-spoonful of Salt.</item>
                        <item>1 Apple or 1 Carrot.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> pint Milk.</item>
                        <item>2 teaspoonfuls Mixed Spice.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Nutmeg.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Baking Powder.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>For this pudding the currants ought to be washed
            and dried, the raisins stoned, and the orange-peel cut up
            in small pieces; grate the lemon rind, and squeeze out
            the juice. If an apple is used, it must be peeled and
            chopped finely, and if a carrot, the red part of it grated.</p>
            <p>Put into a basin all the dry ingredients, including
            the apple, the lemon rind and juice, and mix them them all
            together. Beat the eggs welll, add to them the milk,
            and pour both among the ingredients in the basin,
            mixing thoroughly. Butter a pudding basin or mould
            and pour the pudding in; cover it with a piece of
            buttered paper, and steam for 4 hours.</p>
            <p>Serve hot with either custard or sweet melted butter
            sauce.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Rothesay Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Bread-crumbs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Suet chopped.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of Rasperry Jam.</item>
                        <item>1 teacupful of Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 dessert-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Carbonate of
                        Soda.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful of Vinegar.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Mix in a basin the flour, bread-crumbs, sugar, and
            suet. Stir in the jam and mix well; beat up the egg
            and add the milk to it, and it also into the
            pudding. Wet the carbonate of soda with a very
            little vinegar, just enough to moisten it, and stir it
            thoroughly through all the other ingredients. Pour all
            into a buttered shape. Cover with a buttered paper
            and steam for 2 hours.</p>
            <p>Serve hot with sweet sauce. This pudding is good
            with either white or red gooseberry jam.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Treacle Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 breakfast-cupful of Grated
                        Bread.</item>
                        <item>1 breakfast-cupful of Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Currants.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful Sugar.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Salt.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful Ground Ginger.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Carbonate of Soda.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> teaspoonful Cream of Tartar.</item>
                        <item>1 Egg.</item>
                        <item>Water.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Treacle.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash and dry the currants, and chop up the suet
            very finely.</p>
            <p>Put into a basin all the dry ingredients—the bread,
            flour, sugar, currants, suet, salt, ginger, carbonate of
            soda, and cream of tartar— and mix them well, after
            which add the treacle, stirring it about. Beat up the
            egg and mix it with a teacupful of water; pour this
            in and mix all well together. It should be quite moist
            without being at all sloppy.</p>
            <p>Put it into a shape or basin well rubbed with
            dripping or butter, and cover with a buttered paper.
            Place it in a pot in which there is half an inch of
            boiling water. Put the lid <hi rend="italic">closely</hi> on the pot and
            steam for <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num> hours; then turn out and serve with
            sweet sauce.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—If more water is required to moisten the
            pudding properly, it must be added, but it is best not
            to put more among the egg, in case it should not be
            required.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Bread and Jam Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Bread.</item>
                        <item>Jam.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3/4</num> pint Milk.</item>
                        <item>Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Have a plain round tin or basin that will hold a pint
            and a half (three breakfast-cupfuls), and grease it well
            inside with sweet dripping or butter. Take some very
            thin slices of bread, and spread them with jam; then
            cut them up in slips about 1 inch wide and 3 long.
            Place them lightly in the mould, filling it very nearly
            full. Now beat up 2 eggs well, to which add a
            table-spoonful of sugar and the milk, and after mixing
            all well together, pour into mould. Allow it to
            stand for half-an-hour to soak; then cover the mould
            with a greased paper and place it in a sauce-pan with
            boiling water (the water must reach only half-way up
            the mould); steam for an hour and turn out.</p>
            <p>The pudding must steam very slowly, or the eggs
            will curdle, which would spoil the pudding. Marmalade
            may be substituted instead of jam in this pudding, and
            the bread may be buttered before the jam is put on if
            a richer pudding is desired.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Marmalade Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3/4</num> lb. Bread-crumbs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Marmalade.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful Carbonate of Soda.</item>
                        <item>Butter-milk.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Grate the bread put in a basin; add the suet
            and sugar, and mix well together; then add the
            carbonate of soda, taking care that the lumps are
            rubbed out. Now add the marmalade, and mix; also
            as much butter-milk as will wet the whole, but it
            should not be very moist.</p>
            <p>Grease a basin or mould well and put the pudding
            in; cover with a greased paper, and steam for <num type="fraction">2 1/2</num>
            hours; turn out and serve with sweet sauce, with
            some marmalade mixed to flavour it.</p>
            <p>This pudding, having no egg, is suitable when the
            eggs are objected to, or in winter, when they are very
            expensive.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Urney Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>Flour.</item>
                        <item>Butter.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Sugar.</item>
                        <item>Jam.</item>
                        <item>Carbonate of Soda.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Take 2 eggs, with their weight in butter and flour,
            and the weight of 1 egg in sugar. Put the butter
            and sugar in a basin, and beat them to a cream, add
            the eggs and beat smooth; then add the flour, in which
            should be mixed half a teaspoonful of carbonate of
            soda. Mix till smooth, and add a table-spoonful of
            strawberry or raspberry jam; pour into a buttered
            mould, which cover with a piece of greased paper, and
            steam gently for <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours. Turn out and serve
            with arrowroot sauce.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Tapioca Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Tapioca.</item>
                        <item>2 breakfast-cupfuls of Milk.</item>
                        <item>1 large table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful of Butter.</item>
                        <item>A little Flavouring.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Soak the tapioca for a quarter of an hour in a
            breakfast-cupful of hot water. Put the milk on to boil,
            and when it boils stir in the soaked tapioca, and let it
            also boil, stirring it constantly for nearly 10 minutes.</p>
            <p>Take it off the fire and stir in the sugar, the butter,
            and flavouring; beat up the eggs and add them, stirring
            till quite mixed; then pour into a pudding-dish, and
            bake for half-an-hour.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Fig Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 breakfast-cupful of Bread-crumbs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. Figs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Suet.</item>
                        <item>1 breakfast-cupful of Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 teacupful of Flour.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Sugar.</item>
                        <item>Nutmeg.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Chop up the figs rather finely, and put them in a 
            sauce-pan, with the milk, to stew for a quarter of an
            hour. Put into a basin the bread, flour, and suet
            chopped up finely; also the sugar and a very little
            nutmeg, and mix them well. Add the figs and milk,
            then the eggs well beaten, and whisk all thoroughly
            up with a fork. Butter a basin or shape, and pour
            the pudding in. Place it in a sauce-pan containing a
            little boiling water, and steam for <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours. Serve
            with sweet sauce.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Semolina Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Semolina.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1 1/4</num> pints of Milk.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> oz. Butter.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>2 oz. of Sugar.</item>
                        <item>Flavouring.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Put <num type="fraction">1 1/4</num> pints of milk in a nice clean sauce-pan to
            boil; then sprinkle in the semolina and boil,
            stirring constantly for 5 minutes or rather more;
            then add the sugar and the butter, and mix
            well. Allow it to stand a few minutes in the sauce-pan
            to cool; then beat up the eggs and stir them in,
            mixing thoroughly; add a little flavouring to taste (a
            little grated orange ring or lemon is very pleasant for
            flavouring). Have a plain mould well buttered, and
            ornamented with cherries or raisins; pour the pudding
            in, cover it with buttered paper, and steam for an
            hour; then turn out gently.</p>
            <p>Ground rice is made into a pudding in precisely the
            same way and in the same proportions. Almond flavouring
            is good with rice, or a bay leaf boiled with the milk.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Rice Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 tea-cupful of Whole Rice.</item>
                        <item>2 breakfast-cupfuls of Milk.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Marmalade.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the rice well, and put it on to boil in a small
            pan with a breakfast-cupful of water. Let it boil for
            5 minutes; then pour in the milk, and allow it to boil
            for half-an-hour without stirring it.</p>
            <p>Take the pan from the fire and add the sugar and
            the marmalade, and stir well. Beat up the eggs, and
            add them last, mixing all together; then pour into a
            pudding dish, and bake in the oven or in front of the
            fire for half-an-hour. A hanful of currants may be
            used instead of the marmalade, but they must first be
            washed and dried.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Rice Pudding without Eggs.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. Rice.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Suet.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>Nutmeg.</item>
                        <item>1 handful of Currants.</item>
                        <item>2 breakfast-cupfuls of Milk.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the rice, and put it either into a small pudding-dish
            or pudding-basin; chop up the suet, and add it;
            also the sugar, a very little grated nutmeg and a handful
            of currants well washed. Pour the milk over, and
            put it in a slow oven for <num type="fraction">1 1/2</num> hours; or cover the basin
            with a buttered paper, and place it in a sauce-pan
            with a little water, and steam for an hour.</p>
            <p>This pudding cooks anywhere near the fire where
            the rice can get gradually heated and cooked. Skimmed
            milk does very well, as the suet supplies the want of
            fat both in the rice and te milk, and makes a very
            very rich and good pudding at a small cost. The currants 
            may be omitted.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Roly-Poly Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 breakfast cupful of Flour.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. of Suet finely chopped.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> teaspoonful of Salt.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">3/4</num> teaspoonful Baking Powder.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. of Jam.</item>
                        <item>Butter Milk or Water.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Put the flour into a basin along with the suet
            chopped <hi rend="italic">very</hi> finely, to which add the salt, sugar, and
            baking powder, and mix all well together.</p>
            <p>Now add as much of either butter milk or water as
            will make a stiff paste, gathering up all the flour in the
            basin. Turn it out on the board, and roll it into a thin
            sheet. Take a bowl or plain shape (a melon shape is
            best) and rub it well inside with dripping. Take as
            much of the paste as will line the shape, and fit it
            nicely all round, cutting the edges even. Now put a
            spoonful of jam in the bottom of the shape, and cover
            it with a piece of the paste last, which wet
            round the edges a little to make it adhere. Cover the
            top with a buttered paper, and put the shape into a
            pot with half-an-inch of boiling water in it; put the
            lid of the pot closely on, and steam for 2 hours; then
            turn out.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>—The scraps of paste left after lining the shape
            may be rolled out again, or just put in between the
            layers of jam as they are. Leave a piece the size of
            the top till the last.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Sago Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/4</num> lb. of Sago.</item>
                        <item>2 breakfast-cupfuls of Milk.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                        <item>1 teaspoonful of Butter.</item>
                        <item>Ground Cinnamon.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Wash the sago and pour off the water; then soak it
            in a teacupful of warm water for 10 minutes. Put on
            2 breakfast-cupfuls of skimme dmilk to boil; when it
            boils, stir in the sago and boil for 5 minutes, sittring
            constantly, by which time the sago will be cooked
            enough and quite clear; take the pan from the fire, and
            stir in the sugar and butter. Now beat up the eggs
            and add them, mixing well, and pour the whole into a
            pudding-dish; sprinkle a little ground cinnamon over
            it, and put it on a toaster in front of the fire to brown
            on the top and cook; turn it round once or twice to
            cook evenly, or put it in an oven for half-an-hour.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <div>
                     <head>Black Cap Pudding.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> lb. of Flour.</item>
                        <item>1 table-spoonful Currants.</item>
                        <item>1 pint Milk.</item>
                        <item>2 Eggs.</item>
                     </list>
                     <cb/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 dessert-spoonful of Sugar.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Salt.</item>
                        <item><num type="fraction">1/2</num> teaspoonful Baking Powder.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="indexGroup">
            <div type="index" n="1">
               <head type="main">INDEX.</head>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div>
                        <head>Beverages—</head><!-- for questions -->
                        <list>
                           <item>Apple Water, . . . 117</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="barleyWat">Barley Water . . . 116</seg>,</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#barleyWat">"</seg> Clear, . . 116</item>
                           <item>Black Currant Jam Water, . 115</item>
                           <item>Boston Cream, . . . 117</item>
                           <item>Cocoa, . . . . . 122</item>
                           <item>Coffee, . . . . . 121</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="lem">Lemonade . . . . 115</seg>,</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#lem">"</seg> without Lemon, 115</item>
                           <item>Lemon Syrup, . . . 118</item>
                           <item>Lemon Whey, . . . 118</item>
                           <item>Orange Syrup, . . . 119</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="rasp">Raspberry</seg> Syrup,. . . 119</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#rasp">"</seg> Vinegar, . . 119</item>
                           <item>Rice Water, . , . . 117</item>
                           <item>Strawberry Syrup, . . 119</item>
                           <item>Tea, . . . . . 120</item>
                           <item>Toast and Water, . . 116</item>
                           <item>Treacle Posset, . . . 118</item>
                        </list>
                        </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Cakes and Baking—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Baking Powder, . . . 96</item>
                           <item>Bread, . . . . . 96</item>
                           <item>Buns with Yeast,. . . 98</item>
                           <item>Cream Scones, . . . 108</item>
                           <item>Currant Cake, . . . 104</item>
                           <item>German Sponge Cake,. . 100</item>
                           <item>Ginger Biscuits, . . . 100</item>
                           <item>Gingerbread Cake, . . 99</item>
                           <item>Good Plum Cake, . . 101</item>
                           <item>London Buns, . . . 106</item>
                           <item>Oatmeal Biscuits, . . 107</item>
                           <item>Rock Cakes,. . . . 105</item>
                           <item>Seed Cake, . . . . 100</item>
                           <item>Shortbread, . . . . 107</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="soda">Soda</seg> Scones, . . . 108</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#soda">"</seg> <seg xml:id="cake">Cake</seg>, . . . . 103</item>
                           <item>Sultana <seg copyOf="#cake">"</seg> . . . . 102</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="teacakes">Tea Cakes</seg>, . . . . 105</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#teacakes">"</seg> Light, . . . 103</item>
                           <item>Victoria Biscuits,. . . 101</item>
                           <item>White Cake, . . . 102</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Fish—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item><seg xml:id="hadd">Haddock</seg> or Cod, Boiled, . 27</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#hadd">"</seg> Baked, . . . 27</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="herr">Herrings</seg>, Baked,. . . 30</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#herr">"</seg> Fired,. . . 40</item>
                           <item>Salmon, to Boil,. . . 31</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="saltfish">Salt Fish</seg>, to Cook, . . 28</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#saltfish">"</seg> Pie, . . . 29</item>
                           <item>To Fry Fish, etc., . . 25</item>
                           <item>To Stew Fish, . . . 28</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <cb/>
                     <div>
                        <head>Meats—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>A Good Breakfast Dish, . 50</item>
                           <item>Beef Steak Pie, . . . 43</item>
                           <item>Boiled Meat Pudding,. . 41</item>
                           <item>Breast of Beal Stuffed and
                           Rolled, . . . . 39</item>
                           <item>Cold Meat Mince, . . 57</item>
                           <item>Cold Meat Rolls,. . . 56</item>
                           <item>Curried Rabbit, . . . 52</item>
                           <item>Dutch Stew,. . . 37</item>
                           <item>Fowl Trussed and Boiled, . 49</item>
                           <item>Haricot Mutton, . . . 40</item>
                           <item>Hough Stewed, . . . 45</item>
                           <item>Irish Stew, . . . . 46</item>
                           <item>Kidney Pudding,. . . 48</item>
                           <item>Liver and Bacon,. . . 51</item>
                           <item>Mutton Cutlets, . . . 56</item>
                           <item>Mutton Stuffed and Rolled, 38</item>
                           <item>Ox Kidney Stewed, . . 35</item>
                           <item>Ox Tail Stewed, . . . 34</item>
                           <item>Rabbit Stewed, . . . 35</item>
                           <item>Roast Bullock's Heart, . 49</item>
                           <item>Sausage Rolls, . . . 51</item>
                           <item>Scotch Collop, . . . 46</item>
                           <item>Scotch Haggis, . . . 47</item>
                           <item>Sea Pie, . . . . 55</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="steak">Steak</seg> and Onions Fried, . 44</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#steak">"</seg> Stewed, . . . 42</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#steak">"</seg> Stuffed and Rolled, . 36</item>
                           <item>Toad in a Hole, . . . 47</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="tripe">Tripe</seg> and Onions, . . 53</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#tripe">"</seg> Stewed, . . . 54</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#tripe">"</seg> to Clean, . . . 55</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Miscellaneous—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Omelette, . . . . 128</item>
                           <item>Porridge, . . . . 128</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Preserves—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Apple Jelly,. . . . 123</item>
                           <item>Bramble Jelly, . . . 127</item>
                           <item>Candied Peel, . . . 127</item>
                           <item>Gooseberries, to Bottle, . 125</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="gooseber">Gooseberry</seg> Jam,. . . 123</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#gooseber">"</seg> Jelly,. . . 123</item>
                           <item>Orange Marmalade, . . 126</item>
                           <item>Red Currant Jelly, . . 124</item>
                           <item>Strawberry Jam,. . . 125</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Puddings—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Apple and Orange Fritters,. 85</item>
                           <item>Apple and Rice Meringue, . 87</item>
                           <item>Apple Dumplings, Baked, . 84</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Puddings—<hi rend="italic">Con.</hi></head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Apple Dumplings, Boiled, . 83</item>
                           <item>Apple Pudding, Boiled, . 82</item>
                           <item>Batter and Fruit Pudding, . 80</item>
                           <item>Black <seg xml:id="cappudd">Cap Pudding,</seg> . . 79</item>
                           <item>Bread <seg copyOf="cappudd">"</seg> . . 70</item>
                           <item>Bread and Jam Pudding, . 74</item>
                           <item>Cheese Fritters, . . . 90</item>
                           <item>Corn Flour Shape, . . 81</item>
                           <item>Custard Pudding, . . 87</item>
                           <item>Eve's <seg xml:id="pudd">Pudding,</seg> . . . 90</item>
                           <item>Fig <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . . 76</item>
                           <item>Fish <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . . 26</item>
                           <item>Fruit Tart, . . . . 81</item>
                           <item>Lemon Cream, . . . 88</item>
                           <item>Macaroni and Cheese, . 89</item>
                           <item>Marmalade Pudding,. . 74</item>
                           <item>Pancakes, . . . . 84</item>
                           <item>Plum Pudding, . . . 72</item>
                           <item>Rice <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . . 77</item>
                           <item>Rice and Cheese,. . . 88</item>
                           <item>Rice Pudding without Eggs, 77</item>
                           <item>Roly-Poly Pudding, . . 78</item>
                           <item>Rothesay <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . 72</item>
                           <item>Sago <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . 79</item>
                           <item>Sago and Fruit Pudding, . 85</item>
                           <item>Scrap Bread <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . 71</item>
                           <item>Semolina <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . 76</item>
                           <item>Stewed Prunes, . . . 86</item>
                           <item>Tapioca Pudding, . . 75</item>
                           <item>Treacle <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . . 73</item>
                           <item>Urney <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . . 75</item>
                           <item>Yorkshire <seg copyOf="#pudd">"</seg> . . . 80</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Sauces—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Apple,. . . . . 91</item>
                           <item>Brown,. . . . . 91</item>
                           <item>Clear, . . . . . 92</item>
                           <item>Custard, . . . . 92</item>
                           <item>Egg, . . . . . 92</item>
                           <item>French,. . . . . 91</item>
                           <item>Melted Butter, . . . 93</item>
                           <item>Mint, . . . . . 93</item>
                           <item>Onion or Soubise, . . 94</item>
                           <item>Sweet Melted Butter,. . 93</item>
                           <item>Tomato, . . . . 94</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Sick-Room Cookery—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Apple Fool,. . . . 113</item>
                           <item>Arrowroot, . . . . 114</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="beeft">Beef Tea</seg>, . . . . 110</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#beeft">"</seg> Raw, . . . 111</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#beeft">"</seg> Pudding, . . 112</item>
                           <item>Egg Drink, . . . . 113</item>
                           <item>Flour for Infants' Food, . 112</item>
                           <item>Gruel, . . . . . 114</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <cb/>
                     <div>
                        <head>Sick-Room Cookery—<hi rend="italic">Con.</hi></head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Milk Jelly, . . . . 113</item>
                           <item>Suet and Milk, . . . 114</item>
                           <item>Veal Jelly, . . . . 111</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Soups—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Carrot,. . . . . 18</item>
                           <item>Chicken, . . . 21</item>
                           <item>Cottage, . . . . 13</item>
                           <item>Fisherman's Rice, . . 19</item>
                           <item>German, . . . . 15</item>
                           <item>Green Pea,. . . . 16</item>
                           <item>Haricot Bean, . . . 12</item>
                           <item>Hotch-Potch, . . . 23</item>
                           <item>Kidney, . . . . 21</item>
                           <item>Lentil,. . . . . 14</item>
                           <item>Mutton Broth, . . . 16</item>
                           <item>Onion, . . . . . 22</item>
                           <item>Potato,. . . . . 17</item>
                           <item>Rice, . . . . . 18</item>
                           <item>Skirt, . . . . . 15</item>
                           <item>Stock from Bones, . . 19</item>
                           <item>Tomato, . . . . 20</item>
                           <item>Windsor Milk, . . . 14</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Vegetables—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>Beetroot, to Pickle, . . 67</item>
                           <item>Brussels Sprouts,. . . 62</item>
                           <item>Carrots, to Stes,. . . 61</item>
                           <item>Cauliflower, to Boil, . . 60</item>
                           <item>Green, to Boil, . . . 59</item>
                           <item>Green Peas, to Boil, . . 60</item>
                           <item>Haricot Beans Boiled,. . 62</item>
                           <item>Leeksm to Boil, . . . 65</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="pars">Parsnips,</seg> to Boil,. . . 66</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#pars">"</seg> to Mash, . . 66</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="potat">Potatoes,</seg> to Boil, . . 63</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#potat">"</seg> to Mash, . . 65</item><item></item>
                           <item>Red Cabbage, to Pickle, . 66</item>
                           <item>Spanish Onions, to Boil, . 63</item>
                           <item>Turnips, to Boil and Mash,. 61</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <head>Laundry Work—</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>WASHING— . . . . 131</item>
                           <item>Arrangements for, . . 129</item>
                           <item>Crewel Work, . . . 136</item>
                           <item>Flannel, . . . . 132</item>
                           <item>Lace, . . . . . 135</item>
                           <item>Paraffin Washing, . . 136</item>
                           <item>Prints,. . . . . 134</item>
                           <item>Stockings, . . . . 133</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="whiteclo">White Clothes,</seg> . . . 137</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#whiteclo">"</seg> to Boil, . 138</item>
                           <item>STARCHING— . . . 139</item>
                           <item>Cold-Water Starch, . . 141</item>
                           <item><seg xml:id="shirt">Shirt,</seg> to Starch a, . . 141</item>
                           <item><seg copyOf="#shirt">"</seg> to Iron a, . . . 142</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
	    <table>
           	<row role="label"><cell>Beverages</cell><cell>page</cell></row>
              	<row>
                  <cell>Apple Water</cell>
                  <cell>117</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Barley Water</cell>
                  <cell>116</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
